<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the love of God</title>
            <author>Masham, Damaris, Lady, 1658-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12311175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12311175</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 190:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the love of God</title>
                  <author>Masham, Damaris, Lady, 1658-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Awnsham and John Churchil ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Lady Masham. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Love.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the LOVE OF GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Awnſham</hi> and <hi>John Churchil,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Swan</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:59359:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59359:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Prejudice that Piety and Religion receive by being removed from their true Foundations, is of ſo ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; in diſturbing, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leading, the beſt meaning and moſt ſerious part of Mankind; that any Deſign which tends to prevent Miſtakes about them, will, I hope, at leaſt merit Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. The enſuing Diſcourſe is Publiſh'd with this View: It being intended to ſhow the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceableneſs of an Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis lately recommended to the World for a Ground of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and Morality; As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:59359:3"/>the farther injuriouſneſs of that Hypotheſis to True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Piety: Which, I think, I may ſecurely affirm, neither ever have ſuffer'd, or ever can ſuffer ſo much, from the Arguments of any Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, as from theirs, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by Weakneſs, Vanity, or any other Motive, have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, or pretended to Support them, upon falſe Grounds, and wrong Reaſonings. I am, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, inclined to Believe (as well as Hope) that the Notion which this Diſcourſe is level'd againſt, is in no great danger of being a very general, or prevailing Opinion: It being too Viſionary to be likely to be received by many Intelligent
<pb facs="tcp:59359:3"/>Perſons; And too abſtruſe to be eaſily entertain'd by thoſe who are altogether unconverſant with Scholaſtick Speculations. Yet there are ſo many to whom Novelty alone has ſufficient Charms to recommend any thing, that I cannot but think (if what I have writ anſwers the Intention it was writ with) the Subject of the following Papers very well merited thoſe few Hours that were beſtow'd upon 'em. And I am confirm'd in this Opinion, by that of one of the Higheſt order in our Church; Who (ſince the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them) I was glad to hear ſay, That it would be well done of any one who had leiſure for it, to ſhow the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb facs="tcp:59359:4"/>and extravagance of ſuch of Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s late Practical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes as are built upon the Principles of <hi>Pere Malbranche.</hi> This Incouragement, added to the like from ſome other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, has occaſion'd the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Diſcourſe which was not writ with ſuch an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59359:4"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the Love of God.</head>
            <p>WHatever Reproaches have been made by the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts on the one hand, of the Want of Books of Devotion in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> or by the Diſſenters on the other, of a dead and lifeleſs Way of Preaching; I think it may be affirm'd, That there cannot, any where, be found ſo good a Collection of Diſcourſes upon Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Subjects, as might be made of Engliſh Sermons, and other Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes of that Nature, written by the Divines of our Church: Which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59359:5"/>Books are certainly, in themſelves, of the greateſt and moſt general Uſe of any; and do moſt conduce to that which is the chief Aim of Chriſtianity, a good Life. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe its Profeſſors, divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Parties, may contend about; This they muſt all agree in, That we ought to be a People zealous of good Works.</p>
            <p>Yet tho' no body can deny this; And all are forced to allow, that the Duties of a good Life ought to be practis'd; It is certain, that this which is ſo eſſential to Religion, is ſo far degraded by ſome, as not to paſs for a part of it. They accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly diſtinguiſh a Religious, from a Moral Man; and carry their Zeal for the Doctrinal Part of Religion ſo far, that they ſeem to lay little Streſs on the Performance of thoſe Vertues recommended by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, as the Way to Eternal Life; Which Vertues, have been commonly enough term'd <hi>Splendid Vices,</hi> in thoſe they account not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59359:5"/>true Believers; And the Books writ by others, to recommend the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of them to the World, are look'd upon by theſe Men, as little more worthy of a Chriſtian's Peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, as ſuch, than Hiſtories or Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of humane Prudence.</p>
            <p>But others there are, who do not in this manner undervalue Morality, that yet perhaps are not leſs inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to it; Whilſt they ſtrain the Duties of it to an impracticable Pitch; or pretend to aſcend by it to ſomething beyond, or above it: Which has been mightily the Fault of thoſe in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> Who having a better Reliſh of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, than to be ſatisfied with one conſiſting of nothing but idle, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, and pompous Shows, have betaken themſelves to that which they call the inward Way, or Life of Contemplation: Of which, there never has wanted great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in that Church, known in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times by ſeveral Names, which diſtinguiſh'd them more than their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59359:6"/>Opinions. For in thoſe, they all agreed in one common Difference from all the reſt, though variouſly expreſs'd: And who (whatever their Errours have been) have yet ſeem'd the moſt in earneſt in the Buſineſs of Religion, of any that the Roman Church can boaſt of.</p>
            <p>But however excuſable theſe may be, in regard of their own Church (which perhaps allows them no other Way of being Religious, than that which leads them into theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes) they yet are certainly very injurious to Chriſtianity in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations they make of it; by ſuppoſing, as they do, the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Chriſtian State to conſiſt in Contemplation; And the Duties of a ſocial Life (for which 'tis plain Mankind were intended) to be low Matters, fit only to exerciſe the young Chriſtian, not yet advanced into the ſpiritual State; to which when he arrives, even but to the firſt Degree (for they talk of three Degrees at leaſt of it, by which Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59359:6"/>is to be aſcended to) he then looks down upon all the Duties of the ſecond Table, as an inferiour Diſpenſation, belonging to thoſe of a lower Claſs: And when he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to the higheſt Degree, he is then got above Reaſon it ſelf; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt melted and brought to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and then loſt and ſwallowed up in God. And by theſe, who ſuppoſe themſelves thus far advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Reaſoning, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Diſcourſe, tending to fix our Affections upon God, and expreſſing it ſelf in ſenſible Devotion; and even outward Acts of Obedience to God's Will, are look'd upon as parts of the active Life, and leſs perfect State of a Chriſtian;</hi> as may be ſeen in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Books which treat of this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and particularly in <hi>Santa So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia, Treat.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. Which ſufficiently ſhows of how dangerous Conſequence it is to talk after this Faſhion; and to erect into a Rule, or Diſpenſation of Life, what poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the Experience of ſome (whoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59359:7"/>Circumſtances, or extraordinary Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminations, for ends unknown (and which we have nothing to do with) may have inabled them to give a ſober, and intelligible Senſe of to themſelves; though to others it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Jargon, Enthuſiaſm, or even Irreligion.</p>
            <p>If Books of this kind (which more or leſs thoſe uſually are, the Papiſts call their ſpiritual Books) are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it is well that they are ſo; ſince they would be likely to make many more Enthuſiaſts than good Chriſtians. For as the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> (in his Fanaticiſm of the Roman Church) ſays very well: <hi>If once an unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Way of Practical Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Standard of Devotion, no Men of Senſe and Reaſon will ever ſet themſelves about it; but leave it to be underſtood by mad Men, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd by Fools.</hi> Which is a Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that it were to be wiſh'd all would make, who may be tempted by Affectation of Novelty, Fondneſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59359:7"/>of an Hypotheſis, or any other better Reaſon, to build their Practical and Devotional Diſcourſes upon Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which not only will not bear the Teſt, but which oblige them to lay down ſuch Aſſertions in Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as ſober and well diſpoſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians cannot underſtand to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable: Than which, I think there never was any more evidently ſo, than that Mankind are obliged ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as their Duty, to love with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, nothing but God only; Every Degree of Deſire of any Creature whatſoever, being Sin. This Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though not altogether new, yet has been but lately brought into our Pulpits, and been pretended to be ſet on Foot upon a Philoſophical, or Natural Ground, <hi>viz. That God, not the Creature, is the</hi> immediate, <hi>efficient Cauſe of our Senſations: For whatever gives us Pleaſure</hi> (ſay they who hold this Hypotheſis) <hi>has a right to our Love; but God only gives us Pleaſure, therefore he only has a right to our Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59359:8"/>
            <p>Indeed, in a Sermon upon this Subject, <hi>Matt.</hi> xxij. 37. the Author pretends to eſtabliſh his Senſe of the Words upon a double Baſis. 1. <hi>That God is the only Cauſe of our Love.</hi> 2. <hi>That he is alſo the only proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it.</hi> But in Reference to the firſt, he does no more to this Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but prove what (plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd) cannot be conteſted; <hi>viz.</hi> That we receive the Power which we have of Deſiring, from God: And then asks himſelf ſeveral Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, as, <hi>Can God act for a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? Does not God make all things for himſelf?</hi> &amp;c. Which amount only to thus much, that they ſignifie it is his Opinion, that God (who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs made all things for himſelf) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own Glory was his primary End in creating all things, had not therefore Secondary, and intermediate Ends for which he made the Creatures to operate one upon another: Which is but in a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Way to beg the Queſtion. But he confeſſes rightly, that the Streſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59359:8"/>of this Buſineſs lies in the Proof of the ſecond Propoſition. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Hinge</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the whole Weight of the Theory turns,</hi> viz. That God is the only proper Object of our Love, as being the only Cauſe of all our pleaſing Senſations; the Creatures having no Efficiency at all to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate upon us; they being only occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Cauſes of thoſe Sentiments which God produces in us. And on this Foundation it then is, that he aſſerts, that every Act that carries our Deſires towards the Creature is ſinful: Which Opinion if receiv'd, and follow'd, muſt neceſſarily bring in the like unintelligible Way of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Religion, which the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> has juſtly cenſured in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however perſwaded, either the Author himſelf, or this great Aſſertor of this Hypotheſis are of its Truth, or Reaſonableneſs; As there was no need at all of intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Religion, and Morality, in the Matter; ſo it is alſo very unſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59359:9"/>to them; Since that which they would inferr from it is manifeſtly no juſt Conſequence, any more than a uſeful, or practicable Doctrine. And a Man that had not been migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fond of an Hypotheſis, would never have attempted from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, to fortifie by Scripture, an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſo oppoſite to the Tenour of it; as well as to that Morality which has been ſo excellently preach'd to the World by the Divines of his own Church: Whoſe Diſcourſes are generally, if not univerſally, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this Suppoſition; (or at leaſt imply it) that there may be a lawful Love of the Creatures: And being herein conform'd to right Reaſon, and conſequently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apted to humane Life, they have helped to make ſome Oppoſition to that Irreligion, which by looſeneſs of Manners on the one hand, and uncharitable Zeal on the other, has ſpread it ſelf amongſt us in this laſt Age; But muſt doubtleſs have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed further, had not more reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59359:9"/>Principles of Morality been inculcated into Men, than can be grounded upon ſeeing all things in God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For apparently, if the practical Duties of Religion had not been better accounted for, and inforc'd, than by the ſo much boaſted of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Books of the Roman Church, Religion and Vertue had before this time been diſputed, or ridicul'd, out of our World. And yet any of theſe Books of myſtical Divinity, will be found as well able to ſupport them, as ſome of the late practical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of Mr. <hi>N.</hi> or as any Man's elſe can be, upon the Principle of our being obliged to have no Love of Deſire for any of the Creatures: Which is particularly endeavour'd to be made good in the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd Sermon, upon the great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the Law, <hi>Matt.</hi> xxij. 37. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind.</hi> Wherein the Author pretends to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59359:10"/>ſhow, that all our Love is to be ſo intirely center'd upon God, that not any part of it is to be allow'd to the Creatures.</p>
            <p>But leaſt the inlarging this firſt Commandment to ſuch a Magnitude, ſhould make it ſeem to ſwallow up the ſecond; He prevents that Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by ſhewing, that theſe Two Commandments claſh not at all: The Love of God, and of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, (as he ſays) being different Loves: <hi>For we love God with Love of Deſire; and love, or ſhould love, our Neighbour, only with Love of Benevolence.</hi> Which Diſtinction, in other Diſcourſes of his, he is more large upon; and ſeems to believe the latter part of it confirm'd by theſe Words, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> in <hi>Levit</hi> .xix. repeating to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſundry Laws, and amongſt others, ſeveral ſpecial Duties towards their Neighbour, thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the laſt; (<hi>ver.</hi> the <hi>18th.</hi>) <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59359:10"/>Which Concluſion is comprehenſive of all that preceded it, or that had been omitted; And in a ſhort Rule, better teaches the Extent of what we owe to our Neighbour, than it was poſſible any Enumeration of Particulars could. This Duty is indeed ſo fully expreſs'd herein, that we cannot conceive any Addition could be made to the Perfection of this Precept by our Bleſſed Saviour; Who came to teach us the whole Will of the Father, and to give us the moſt perfect Rule of Life that had yet been delivered to Mankind; and accordingly, <hi>Luke</hi> the <hi>4th. ch. v.</hi> 25. being asked, <hi>Maſter what ſhall I do to inherit Eternal Life?</hi> He ſaid, <hi>How readeſt thou in the Law?</hi> It being anſwer'd, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, with all thy Mind, and with all thy Strength; and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf:</hi> He replied, <hi>Thou haſt anſwer'd right; This do, and thou ſhalt live.</hi> He had anſwer'd right, in joining together theſe two
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59359:11"/>Commandments in the Law, <hi>on which all the reſt of the Law and Prophets did depend,</hi> Matt. xxij. 40. And our Saviour aſſures him the Rule of the Law was in neither part ſhort, or defective: For he ſays, <hi>This do, and thou ſhalt live.</hi> We are here taught, that the Love of God, and of our Neighbour, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes the whole of our Duty: And accordingly we are elſe-where alſo told, <hi>That Love is the fullfilling of the Law.</hi> Its Regulation therefore is certainly of the utmoſt Conſequence to us; And the Meaſures of it are, <hi>That we love God with all our Heart, with all our Souls, with all our Mind, and with all our Strength; and our Neighbour as our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Precepts are joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Goſpel, and there is a very near Affinity between them. But they are not ſo joined in the Law from whence they are cited; Neither is there any Appearance that thoſe to whom they were there given underſtood, or could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59359:11"/>by them, the Love of God and the Love of their Neighbour <hi>to be diſtinct Affections, differing in kind;</hi> as is affirm'd by Mr. <hi>N.</hi> Who in Purſuance of (at beſt) a uſeleſs Notion, would take from a great part of Mankind their only ſure Retreat, when bewildered in the Maze of Opinions, endleſly conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the Men of Skill in Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: He having done as much to perplex the plain Duties of Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as others have done the ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative parts of Religion. But there appears no Ground from the Text here, to affirm that the Command of loving their Neighbour as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, was (as he ſays it was) <hi>not only an abſolute Meaſure, but a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Character put in on purpoſe to diſtinguiſh it from their Love of God, Page</hi> 165. of his Philoſophical and Divine Letters: Unleſs that Mr. <hi>N.</hi> will ſay, that the Words neceſſarily imply ſo much; which is to beg the thing he conteſts for, and not to prove it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59359:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaking as a Law-giver, to a Multitude that did not much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine in their Speculations, or diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh things with Philoſophical Niceneſs, ſeems very plainly by this Text (as the foregoing ones make it evident) to deſign only to tell them how far the Love of their Neighbour ought to extend: As not only to the doing no Injury (ſpecified in ſundry Inſtances) but even to the <hi>bearing no Grudge;</hi> And (Finally ſays he) <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> That is, do him as little Harm, and as much Good, as thou deſireſt ſhould be done to thy ſelf. Whether, or no, he ſhould be the Object of Deſire, is not determined by this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, any farther than as Love na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally draws Deſire after it. But againſt the Lawfulneſs of any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's being deſired by us, it is ſaid by Mr. <hi>N. That as we cannot love God with a Love of Benevolence, he wanting nothing to be wiſhed to his Perfection, and Happineſs; ſo we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59359:12"/>ought not to love the Creature with a Love of Deſire, they being uncapable to make any part of our Happineſs.</hi> What we cannot do, we are certain we ſhall not: And we need little Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to deſire what is not deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, or (which is here equivalent) not pleaſing to us. But though Men may poſſibly (in the Ignorance they are in of their own Being, and the Conſtitution of other things, with their mutual Relations) mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, that which can make them finally happy; yet none can be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed not to know what, at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, pleaſes them; which is the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, or Pleaſure here intended. How little it ſignifies to this Matter (though the Streſs of the Aſſertion lies in it) to ſay, That <hi>ſenſible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are not the efficient, but occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Cauſes of our pleaſing Senſations,</hi> will ſoon be conſider'd. But if when we uſe the Word <hi>Love,</hi> we reflected what it is we mean by it, we ſhould perhaps be more inlighten'd than by Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s Definition of it, and ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59359:13"/>learn to diſtinguiſh better, than to call different Paſſions by the ſame Name; or confound Love, with whatever is a Concomitant of it.</p>
            <p>When I ſay that I love my Child, or my Friend, I find that my Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that they are things I am delighted in; Their Being is a Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to me.</p>
            <p>When I ſay that I love God above all, I find I would expreſs that he is my chiefeſt Good, and I delight in him above all things.</p>
            <p>Again, when I ſay that I love my ſelf, I likewiſe mean by it that my Being is dear, and pleaſing to me. To ſay one loves a thing, and that it is that which one has Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſency in, is juſt the ſame: Love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only a Name given to that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or Act of the Mind, we find in our ſelves towards any thing we are pleas'd with; And ſo far as it is ſimply Love, conſiſts barely in That; and cannot be diſtinguiſh'd into different Acts of wiſhing well, and deſiring; which are other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59359:13"/>Acts of the Mind, conſequential to Love, according to the difference of the Object. To intelligent Beings that we love, our Love is follow'd with acts of Benevolence, or wiſhing well to the Being, and Happineſs of that thing that helps to make us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; and with deſire of injoying that in them that delights us: And our Love to Inanimate things is follow'd with Benevolence and Well wiſhing to their Being, if it may be continued with their Injoyment; and with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire alſo of injoying them. But, becauſe Benevolence appears moſt in Wiſhing Happineſs to Beings capable of it; And the uſe of moſt Inanimate things which we love and deſire to injoy, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys them in the Injoyment; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Learned Men have talk'd as if there were two ſorts of Love Whereas Love is but one ſimple act of the Mind, always accompanied with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and Benevolence too, where the Object is capable of it. But as that Definition which Mr. <hi>N.</hi> has given us, (viz. <hi>That Love is that Original Weight, Bent or Indeavour, whereby the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59359:14"/>Soul ſtands inclin'd to, and is mov'd for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to Good ingeneral, or Happineſs</hi>) tells as not ſo well what Love is, as our own Hearts can when we conſult them; So perhaps an Examination of them will not only better acquaint us with the Nature of our Paſſions; but alſo direct us better to the Meaſures of their Regulation, than Notions concerning them deduced from the Conſequences of an Hypotheſis.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore conſider more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, how by the different Objects of our Love our Hearts are affected.</p>
            <p>When we ſay we love our ſelves Have we then only a ſimple Percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Pleaſure, and Complaiſance in our Being? Or is any thing elſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd to that Pleaſure as a neceſſary Concomitant, or Conſequence of it Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays, (<hi>Letters Philoſophical and Divine,</hi> p. 165.) that <hi>our love of our ſelves is not love of Deſire, but love of Benevolence moſt undoubtedly.</hi> Moſt undoubtedly theſe words of Mr. <hi>N.</hi> very much claſh with what he affirms elſewhere (ſee his <hi>Theory and Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Love,</hi> p. 14. and 15.) where
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59359:14"/>having reduced or comprehended Love under Concupiſcence and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, he expreſly tells us, that <hi>There is no deſire without Benevolence, and no Benevolence without define.</hi> But he does not in this oppoſe himſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but Truth alſo ſince the deſire of the continuation of our Being is truly a Deſire of our Selves, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ſomething of our ſelves which we have not already: As he that having Light and Warmth enough of the Sun, deſiring its Continuation, deſires more of the Sun than he has already. The Continuation of our Being is neceſſary to our Happineſs in the Beatifick Viſion: And if we deſire more of that Happineſs by only deſiring the Continuation of it, we certainly deſire more of our ſelves, by deſiring the Continuation of our Being.</p>
            <p>Let us farther obſerve, how our Hearts are affected in our love of other things. Our Being, we evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently find ſtands in need of other Beings for its Support and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; becauſe it is not ſufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59359:15"/>for either: And therefore to the Complaiſance or Pleaſure we have in it, we find neceſſarily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd a wiſhing to it whatever we conceive may either continue, or improve it.</p>
            <p>As to God himſelf, whom Mr. <hi>N.</hi> makes the ſole Object of our Deſires; I wiſh Mr. <hi>N.</hi> had a little more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd himſelf what he means by our Deſiring of God. For the Perfection and Superlativeneſs of his Nature, makes him the Object of our Love, Deſire and Benevolence, in a quite different way from Created Beings. We love God for thoſe Excellencies of his Nature, wherein he infinitely ſurpaſſes all that is good, or deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the Creature. When we are ſaid to Deſire him, I think we mean ſuch a Communication of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whereby he beſtows on us any Degree of Happineſs: And in this ſenſe, we ſhall to Eternity deſire more and more of him.</p>
            <p>But he being both Neceſſary and Perfect, we can therefore wiſh no good to him, which he has not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59359:15"/>Becauſe we cannot conceive any Addition of Good can be made to him. Our Benevolence is limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his perfect Nature, only to Acts of Joy and Complaiſance in his Perfections, which is all we can do; But the doing of That declares, That if any thing could be added to his Perfection and Happineſs, we ſhould wiſh it. And therefore, as an Expreſſion of that Benevolence, it is made our Duty to give him Praiſe, and as much as we can to Glorifie him.</p>
            <p>Again, When we ſay, That we love our Children, or Friends; It is evident alſo from the Nature of the Object, that we not only wiſh to them as to our ſelves, whatever we conceive may tend to continue, or improve their Being; but alſo, that Deſire of them is a neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant of our Love: Becauſe we are not always preſent with them, whereby we ſhould enjoy them more: And it is impoſſible to love the Preſence, or Kindneſs of any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59359:16"/>thing, without deſiring to poſſeſs it. Now, If any one will ſay, we ought not to be ſo pleaſed; They then deny that we ought to love: For we cannot love but what we are pleaſed with. It is true, that every one may apply words as they think fit; But then others ought to take care not to be impoſed on by them. And if any one will either tell us, That we love things in which we find no Pleaſure; Or, That being pleaſed with a thing, we do not yet love it; Or will call different Paſſions by the ſame Name; Or imply in the word <hi>Love,</hi> that complication of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paſſions inſeparable, indeed, from Love, but varying according to the Objects of it; It will concern us to examine what they ſay, before we receive their Dictates, as Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for the Regulation of a Paſſion, upon the right Regulation of which depends both our Preſent, and Future Happineſs.</p>
            <p>Love is but one ſimple Act of the Mind: But whether our deſiring
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59359:16"/>of what we love, or only wiſhing well to it, or both, follows that act of Love; the Nature of the lov'd Object alone Determines. For if that be both capable of being a good to us, and of receiving good from us, or from any thing elſe, it is then certain that we wiſh both: If it be capable of but one, and we know it to be ſo, it is certain we can then wiſh but one. The Diſtinction which is made of love of Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and Concupiſcence, (ariſing only from the different Natures of the Objects of our Love) is only the Miſ-application of the word Love to different acts conſequent to Love, but diſtinct from it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on the different Nature of the Object.</p>
            <p>But it is ſaid, That <hi>no Creature is capable of being a Good to us.</hi> Every Man's Experience confutes this eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day, and would do ſo, although that were true that theſe Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for; which therefore cannot in the leaſt tend to promote Piety.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59359:17"/>
            <p>It is certain, that to believe (which is evidently true) that we receive all our Good from the Hand of God; ought to be, and effectively is, the proper Ground of our Love of Him above all things. But that we do receive all our good from the Hand of God, is equally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged whether we believe the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture receives an Efficiency from God to excite pleaſing Senſations in us; Or that God himſelf exhibiting part of his Eſſence to us, at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Creature, is himſelf the immediate Author of thoſe Pleaſing Senſations: Which is the Hypotheſis propoſed for the Advancement of the Love of God.</p>
            <p>But as Truth of no kind is ever advantaged by Falſhood; ſo alſo, it ſeems a reſpect Due to ſo important, and withal, ſo evident a Duty as the Love of God, not needleſly to lay the ſtreſs of it upon any Doubtful, Unintelligible, or Precarious Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis; whatever Pretences it carries with it of Piety.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59359:17"/>
            <p>Pompous Rhapſodies of the Soul's debaſing her ſelf, when ſhe deſcends to ſet the leaſt part of her Affections upon any thing but her Creator, (however well they may poſſibly be intended) are plainly but a comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting God with the contempt of his Works, by which we are the moſt effectually led to Know, Love, and Adore him. And ſuch kind of Expreſſions as carry not a Relative, but Abſolute Abhorrence, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Injoyments the moſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſeem only allowable, as unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated Raptures of Devout Minds, not the Productions of Philoſophical Diſquiſition; and will only affect thoſe that are truely Pious, whilſt they carry a ſhow of ſome Truth in the Heart of the Speaker, which they ſtrictly have not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For 'tis not unlikely that a lively Remorſe may ſo turn the Stream of ſome Men's Affections from all ſenſible Pleaſures, and give them ſo ſtrong a Diſguſt for them, that the very Remembrances and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59359:18"/>Ideas of thoſe Pleaſures, even where allowable, may become Ungrateful: As Men have often Averſion to ſee or hear of Places or Perſons, (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Dear to them) by which, or in which, they have ſuffer'd much. The Paſſions where they are ſtrong, argue by a Logick of their own, not that of Reaſon, which they often and ſignificantly enough, invert to ſerve their own Purpoſe. And when Religion is in the caſe (with which too many are perſwaded Reaſon has little to do) they can eaſily advance this ſo far, as to dreſs out an intire Syſtem, intelligible only by Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not to Reaſon; of which, perhaps ſome of the Myſtical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines are an Example. But to what Extravagance ſoever this may be carried, it is not therefore to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, That he who requires the Service of the whole Man, rejects the Paſſions from bearing a part; whilſt we ſuffer them neither to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon our ſelves, nor others, to the admitting of wrong Notions,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59359:18"/>Prejudicial to true Religion. And it is likely, that many People of weak Underſtandings, may owe moſt of their Religion to their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; It being certain, that if ſome Men had no more Religion than they are capable of having by a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Diſquiſition, it muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding little.</p>
            <p>But whenever any one pretends to preſcribe Meaſures of Duty, not ſuited to a Popular Audience, but ſuch as ſhall challenge the ſtricteſt Attention and Scrutiny of Reaſon, he ought to exclude all Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor and Hyperbole. For thoſe Notions will deſervedly be ſuſpected of ſome Defect, which are uſher'd in, or attended with Flights, not only out of the reach of common Senſe, but which oppoſe the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of Mankind; As all ſuch do that have for Foundation the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's being uncapable to procure us any good: There being none of them, perhaps, that we approach, which either does not, or may not,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59359:19"/>contribute to our Good, or Ill; And which truly are not in Effect al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to do ſo, by thoſe who deny them to be Efficient Cauſes. For it will be found to amount to the ſame thing in regard of us, and our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to deſire them, whether they are Efficient, or Occaſional Cauſes, of our pleaſing Senſations: The proof of which laſt Opinion, (taken from their own Ignorance of any other way to explain the Nature of our Ideas, and Perceptions) They can hardly feel the force of; Without having a great Opinion of their own Faculties, or a very ſmall one of the Power, and Wiſdom of God. And they muſt alſo be very clear ſighted, if they can diſcern how this Hypotheſis of ſeeing all things in God, helps us one jot further in the Knowledge of our Ideas, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions; which is the thing it was Primarily pretended to be deſign'd for. They who advance this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do only fetch a Circuit, and then return where they were before,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59359:19"/>without gaining any advantage, by Derogating (as they do) from the Wiſdom of God, in framing his Creatures like the Idols of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, that have Eyes, and ſee not; Ears, and hear not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we are only now concern'd, to inquire of what Uſe this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is in Morality; That any one ſhould be zealous in aſſerting it on that account.</p>
            <p>The Creatures they ſay are occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Cauſes of our pleaſing Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Then, however, they are Cauſes of them. They deny not alſo, That they are ſuch Cauſes as are always accompanied with the Effect, and without which the Effect is not produced. And are they not then conſider'd as Goods to us, juſt the ſame as if they were efficient Cauſes? Or muſt we think a beautiful Flower has not the ſame Appearance, whether it be believ'd that God has lodg'd a power in the Flower to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the Idea of its Colour in us, or that he himſelf exhibits the Idea of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59359:20"/>its Colour at the preſence of that Object? If the Flower is either way equally pleaſing (as certainly it is) then it is alſo equally deſireable. But the Wiſdom of God cannot herein be equally admired, becauſe it is not equally conſpicuous. For if God immediately exhibits to me all my Idea's, and that I do not truly ſee with my Eyes, and hear with my Ears; then all that wonderful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs and curious Workmanſhip, in framing the Organs of Senſe, ſeems ſuperfluous and vain; Which is no ſmall Reflection upon infinite Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>We are moreover told, That the whole of our Duty, and Happineſs, conſiſts in making God the ſole Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Deſires; <hi>The leaſt ſpark of which ſacred Fire cannot light upon the Creatures, without ſo far defrauding him:</hi> And that the Reaſon of this Duty is, becauſe <hi>the Creatures are not the efficient Cauſes of our Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> If this be ſo, this ſeems alſo to lay an Imputation upon the Wiſdom
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59359:20"/>and Goodneſs of God, who has laid the Foundation of our Duty in a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which he has concealed from us. For this great Cauſe why we ſhould love him alone, (<hi>viz. becauſe the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not the efficient Cauſes of our Senſations</hi>) is ſo hidden from us by all the Art, and Contrivance, obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in Nature, that if it were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely deſign'd to be conceal'd, and we purpoſely intended to be miſled, it could not be more ſo. For in Effect till this laſt Age, it has not been diſcover'd; Or at leaſt very ſparingly; And even ſtill (as it ſeems) only Heads caſt in <hi>Metaphyſical Moulds</hi> are capable of it. This, I ſay, one would think were ſome Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon the Divine Wiſdom; Yet no leſs than this is ſaid. For the whole of our Duty is placed in a right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation of our Love: The whole of that Regulation in making God the ſole Object of our Deſires; And having only Charity, or Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, for his Creatures. And this Diſtribution is grounded on no clear
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59359:21"/>Text of Scripture; Nor on other Foundation from Reaſon, than this only, That the Creatures are not the efficient Cauſes of our pleaſing Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations.</p>
            <p>Indeed, ſometimes, the Severity of ſome Precepts of Morality may well be thought to have been a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the Diſcovery of their Truth; And this of Centring all our Affections upon God, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the leaſt part of our Deſires to run out after ſenſible Goods, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at firſt Sight, a ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being of that Nature. And doubtleſs, with many plain, well-meaning People, (who underſtood not the Metaphyſical Ground of it, But endeavour'd to practiſe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pretending to prove it) it tended to great Auſterities; ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps Uſeful; but moſt commonly Superſtitious, and Pernicious to true Religion. But a late Teacher of this Doctrine, tho' he has advanced the Theory, is more favourable in the practical part, than to recommend
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59359:21"/>by it any ſuch Popiſh Mortifications and Severities: And he, with great Reaſon, ſeems to believe, that the good things of this World were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be enjoyed by us. No Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he ſays, indeed, can be Loved, or Deſired, without <hi>Defrauding God, and even committing the Sin of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> Vol. III. <hi>Practical Diſcourſe,</hi> p. 62.67. Conſequently therefore, there can be no more hateful Sin to the Almighty than (feeling Cold, or Hunger) to deſire Fire, or Food, as any good to us: But he tells us at the ſame time, That tho' the things which ſatisfie theſe Natural Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings are by no means to be deſired as Goods; <hi>Yet they may be ſecurely ſought for as ſuch, and enjoyed,</hi> p. 73, 74. He whoſe <hi>Head is caſt in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſical Mould</hi> has, it may be, Privileges of Nature which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it, that ordinary Mortals are Strangers to; Who tho' they can conceive indeed a thing to be lov'd without being ſought, or to be ſought without being lov'd; Yet from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59359:22"/>the Frailty of their own Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will ſcarce ever be perſwaded in Fact that they, and this Author, being thoroughly Cold, ſeek for Fire, upon different Motives; Or will think that He being truly Hungry, ſeeks Food only upon a prudential Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and not out of any Deſire that he has to the Meat; Should he tell them ever ſo much, That the Mind of Man, conſcious of its own Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Innate Nobleneſs, ought not to debaſe it ſelf to ſuch mean Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as the Love of any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>The Creatures being no more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to pleaſe any Faculty than to Create it; And therefore have no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to the leaſt Intereſt in our Love,</hi> Prac. D. <hi>p.</hi> 59. And it will even not be eaſie for him to perſwade them, That he does not, in this, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the Wiſdom of his Creator, and reproach God for not having made him as he ought to have done. For Men are very ſeldom talk'd out of their Senſes. And if they ſhould not want the Charity to believe him
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59359:22"/>ſincere; they will yet alſo be very ready to conclude him unacquainted with the World, and Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to judge of that of others by his own extraordinary, and Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>But the Words of the Text, <hi>Matt.</hi> xxij. 37. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind,</hi> he ſays, will admit of no other good Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation than that God is ſolely, and only, to be Loved: <hi>Since with no to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Senſe he can be ſaid to Love God with all his Soul, and all his Mind, that only loves him above other things; Allowing other things at the ſame time a ſhare in his Love,</hi> p. 10. <hi>The higheſt Senſe,</hi> he thinks, <hi>that is generally put upon theſe Words amounts to no more than this: That God is to be the Prime, and Principal, Object of our Love, and Delight: That we are to Love him in a ſuperlative way above all other things whatſoever, ſo as to loſe any Good, or ſuffer any Evil, rather than commit the leaſt Sin againſt him:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59359:23"/>That we are always to preferr him in our Love, chuſing to obey him rather than Man, and to pleaſe him rather than ſatisfie our own Will, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy him rather than any Worldy or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Pleaſure,</hi> p. 5, 6. But this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, he thinks, <hi>exhauſts not the Senſe of the Commandment; ſince no Logick, or Grammar, can bear to call the Part, though the larger Part, the whole,</hi> p. 10. But it is not the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether Logick, or Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, will bear calling the Part the whole; but whether every Text in Scripture is to be interpreted by his Logick, and Grammar: Or whether, in ſome Caſes, Scripture does not accommodate it ſelf to the faſhion, and figurative ways of ſpeaking uſual amongſt Men; Which when rightly, not literally underſtood, are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Logick, and Grammar. This it is plain the Opinion of the Divines, and other Learned Men is, That the Scripture does ſo accommodate it ſelf: Becauſe they have interpreted this Text, and not this alone, but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59359:23"/>others alſo in ſuch a Senſe. And therefore if he would put any Streſs upon this Argument, he muſt firſt ſhow that thoſe are miſtaken who think that Scripture oftentimes ſpeaks figuratively and popularly; which is ſo receiv'd an Opinion, that to oppoſe it as he does (or elſe ſays nothing to the Purpoſe) without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any reaſon at all, in this place, for ſo doing, ſeems to argue more Arrogancy than Impartiality in the ſearch of Truth. Now if Scripture does ſometimes accommodate it ſelf to the ordinary ways of ſpeaking amongſt Men; Why ſhould it not be thought to do ſo in this Text? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the common Senſe of Mankind oppoſes any other Meaning as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than that which is familiar to us. For it cannot be deny'd, that, in every Language, nothing is more ordinary than to ſay we love a Perſon intirely, or with all our Hearts, when we love them very much; And yet better may this be ſaid, if we love them above all others. And as we mean
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59359:24"/>no more than one of theſe two things, by theſe Expreſſions, ſo we deſign not to be underſtood otherwiſe: And this is ſo well known, that we are alſo never miſtaken in them.</p>
            <p>But it is yet more evident, that this Text is to be underſtood in the familiar Senſe of the Words; If it be remembred that they are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of a Law-Maker (<hi>Deut.</hi> vi. 5. from whence our Saviour cites them) to a Rude, and Illiterate Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Now the Duty that theſe Words injoins, Mr. <hi>N.</hi> himſelf confeſſes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be carried higher than the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters have carried it (viz. <hi>to Love God ſupremely, and above all things</hi>) <hi>without building in the Air; Unleſs his Hypotheſis be received:</hi> Which unleſs he will ſay <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> he makes him an admirable Lawgiver, to deliver to his People the moſt Eſſential of all his Laws, ſo as it was not, or cannot be thought, likely that one of a Hundred, if at leaſt any one amongſt them, did underſtand it. For I ſuppoſe it will
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59359:24"/>not be deny'd by Mr. <hi>N. That though by the Parturiency of his own Mind, he very early light upon this Notion,</hi> and was not (as the World imagines he was) beholden to <hi>Pere Malbranche</hi> for it; That the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> generally were not ſo ſpeculative, and philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical as he, in their Natural Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius; And yet leſs, that they either Cultivated any ſuch Speculations in the time of <hi>Moſes;</hi> Or had any Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or receiv'd Opinion amongſt them, <hi>That the Creatures were not Efficient, but Occaſional Cauſes of their Pleaſing Senſations;</hi> by which they might be enabled to underſtand this Command concerning loving God. not in the familiar, and conceivable Senſe of the Words, but in Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s Logical, and Grammatical, though otherwiſe Inconceivable Senſe of them.</p>
            <p>But beſides that Lawgivers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways give their Laws in the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar manner they can; The Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs alſo of Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s Senſe of the Words as a Moral Rule, is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59359:25"/>reaſon in it ſelf why <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould not be underſtood according to his Explanation; Which puts a Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Command that is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently, and plainly impracticable: <hi>viz.</hi> That God is ſo wholly to be loved, that it is <hi>defrauding Him,</hi> to place the leaſt Degree of our Love upon the Creatures; And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though they may be ſought and injoyed by us as Goods, yet they cannot be deſired by us as ſuch, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin. This Inconceivableneſs of any other Senſe, that could (by his Auditors at leaſt) be put upon his Words; might, I doubt not, in any other Caſe, plead <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Excuſe to Mr. <hi>N.</hi> himſelf, for having thus tranſgreſs'd, as he thinks, againſt Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick and Grammar, whilſt he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd himſelf in a way, that may well be ſuppos'd to have been as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and uſual then, as it is now. It is to be hoped, that to many others he will not need excuſe in this, wherein, (with what has a Natural Connexion, and is accordingly, out
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59359:25"/>of <hi>Moſes,</hi> joined to it by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) he has ſo well comprehended the Duty of Mankind, that Chriſt ſays, <hi>This do, and thou ſhalt live:</hi> That is, <hi>Love the Lord thy God with all thy Soul, with all thy Heart, with all thy Mind, and with all thy Strength: And thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Commands have no Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, or Difficulty at all to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, if we have honeſt Hearts, and Heads not poſſeſs'd with an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis which every thing muſt be made to chime to. For to love any thing with all our Hearts, is in its known and uſual Signification, to love it a dently. <hi>Moſes</hi> joins to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God with all our Hearts, loving him alſo, with all our Souls, and all our Minds; That is, with all the Faculties of our reaſonable Nature. And by this, we are taught not only to love him very ardently, but above all other things; As being our Creator, and great Benefactor, upon whom we depend every Moment, and from whom we receive all the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59359:26"/>Good that we injoy, and from whoſe Bounty we expect all that we hope for; As alſo, as being every way in himſelf infinitely (beyond all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Compariſon) a Being the moſt lovely. Fooliſh Men (too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Experience ſhows) love ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently oftentimes, without conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whether the Object of their Love be worthy of it. But <hi>to love with the Mind and the Soul,</hi> as well as the Heart, is not to love ſo; but to love with the Underſtanding, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, as well as Paſſionately. And we cannot Love God with our <hi>Souls and with our Mind,</hi> that is, with the Application of our Underſtandings, and with a reaſonable Love, without loving him above all his Creatures; Becauſe he is infinitely more lovely; And every ones reaſon, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults it, muſt always aſſent that he is ſo.</p>
            <p>The Duty then that we are taught is plainly what reaſon requires, <hi>viz.</hi> That we love the moſt lovely Being above all others; And that all the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59359:26"/>Powers, and Faculties of our Mind, conſent in this Preference of him: That we think of him (as well as we are able) as he is; and pay the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Tribute of Affection, and Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to him that our Natures are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. This is alſo plainly Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, and what we may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we perform or no, by asking our ſelves, whether we are willing to part with any other Good for the Sake of this; (as Father, Mother, Husband, Wife, or Children, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>) Which our Saviour tells us, whoever is not ready to part with for his Sake is not worthy of him; But that whoſoever parts with any of theſe for the Goſpel's Sake, ſhall receive manifold Reward, both in this Life, and in the World to come. Now if none of theſe were allow'd to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable to us, but to be only Objects of our Charity (as Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays they ought to be) Why ſhould we deſerve ſo great Reward for forſaking of them for God's Sake? And why ſhould our Saviour, as he plainly does, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59359:27"/>the Deſireableneſs of theſe things to us, if they were not in ſome Degree allow'd to be deſired?</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays, we are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Love our Neighbour, as our ſelves;</hi> And that it being plain, that we do not love our ſelves with a Love of Deſire, therefore it is plain that we ought not to love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> in <hi>Levit.</hi> xix. from whence the above cited Text is taken, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rehears'd divers other Laws to the People, comes to tell them what they owe to their Neighbour; which he does from the 13 to the <hi>18th.</hi> Verſe; with which he thus concludes: <hi>Thou ſhalt not avenge, nor bear any grudge againſt the Children of thy People. But thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> The Senſe of theſe Words could not be miſtaken by any one who was not prepoſſeſs'd with an Hypotheſis, which he was willing to ſupport from Scripture Authority. For <hi>Moſes</hi> having told the People, That <hi>they ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59359:27"/>their Neighbour; That they ſhould not mock at his Infirmities: That they ſhould not oppreſs him; But judge in Righteouſneſs, not reſpecting the Perſon of the Poor or the Rich; That they ſhould not only not ſtand againſt the Blood of their Neighbour; But alſo, not hate him in their Heart;</hi> And further, That they ſhould not only take care of his Temporal Wellfare, but alſo of his Spiritual; By <hi>rebuking him when he ſins;</hi> And likewiſe, be ſo far from avenging themſelves when injured by him, that <hi>they ſhould not ſo much as bear a Grudge againſt him;</hi> He concludes all with that which ought to be the Spring from which all theſe good Offices to our Neighbour ſhould proceed; and which in ſhort, fully teaches us the Extent of our Duty to him: <hi>Thou ſhalt Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> That is, plainly, That as we love our ſelves; and from that Principle of Love, do good to our ſelves; ſo we ſhould alſo love our Neighbour, and from that Principle
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59359:28"/>of Love to him, ſhould do him all the good that we can: Not only barely performing towards him the outward Acts of thoſe Duties here injoined, or any other; But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them upon the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Delight, and Complaiſance in his well being which we have in our own; Without which, all our Performances will be defective.</p>
            <p>We muſt here conſider, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaking either as a Lawgiver, or as a Philoſopher. If as the Firſt, then without doubt he muſt be thought to have ſpoke ſo, as the People whom he ſpoke to could the eaſilieſt apprehend him. And the whole Scope of his Diſcourſe, makes the above-mentioned Senſe of his Words plainly the moſt obvious meaning of them, <hi>viz.</hi> That as People love themſelves, and upon that Principle of Love do good to themſelves; So alſo it is their Duty to love their Neighbour; without which, they cannot diſcharge what they owe to him. Neither could any other Senſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59359:28"/>be put upon the Words of <hi>Moſes, Thou ſhalt Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> Without the Learned Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Love of Benevolence, and Love of Concupiſcence; Which it is hard to believe, That Mr. <hi>N,</hi> or any one elſe can think many, if any, of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were acquainted with. Tho' if he could ſuppoſe they had been ſo, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf had had Regard to it; and had alſo Philoſophiz'd as ill as the People; I wonder Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſhould not ſee that it would yet make nothing to his purpoſe: Since <hi>Moſes</hi> is not here tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them all that they lawfully may do, but all that they neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily muſt do, not to fail in their Duty.</p>
            <p>But if Mr. <hi>N.</hi> had rather <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould be conſider'd here, ſpeaking as a Philoſopher, according to, (and inſtructing the People in) the true Nature of things; as well as laying down Precepts for them to obey; It is then more evident, That the Words of <hi>Moſes</hi> will not only not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59359:29"/>comply with the Senſe He puts upon them, but alſo that they are oppoſite to it. For <hi>Moſes</hi> ſays, <hi>Thou ſhalt Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf:</hi> That is, thou ſhalt take the ſame Complaiſance, in the Being, and well Being of thy Neighbour, as in thy own. Now it is manifeſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and contradictious, that we ſhould rejoice, and take Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, in what is no way deſireable to us: Or that we ſhould not deſire that in which we rejoice, and take Complaiſance. The Being therefore, and well Being of our Neighbour; muſt neceſſarily be deſireable to us; and we could not otherwiſe love him as our ſelves. For it is certain, That our own Being, and well Being, are deſirable to us: (Who is there that does not deſire the Continuation of them?) And therefore that there is no Love without Deſire, any more than without Benevolence (as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent in our Love of God) ſo far as the Objects of our Love admits of both.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59359:29"/>
            <p>But Love ſimply, as is above ſaid, is that Diſpoſition, or Act, of the Mind, which we find in our ſelves towards any thing we are pleas'd with; and conſiſts barely in that Diſpoſition, or Act; And cannot be diſtinguiſh'd into different Acts of wiſhing well, or Benevolence; And Deſiring: Which are other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Acts of the Mind, exerted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the different Objects of our Love. We deſire to injoy in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, that in them which delights us: And we wiſh well to the Being of every thing that helps to make us happy. If their Being can be continued with our Injoyment of them; that Injoyment is alſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily deſired by us: It being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any Creature not to Deſire whatever appears to them to make a part of their Happineſs.</p>
            <p>But now whence is it that ariſes either thoſe Wars, and Violences, that are in the World amongſt Men one with another; or thoſe Tumults and Perturbations, that too frequently
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59359:30"/>ſpring up in their own Breaſts, when all things without them are Serene, Peaceable, and Quiet? From Deſire, it is true, all theſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs proceed: And Deſire is the inexhauſtible Fountain of Folly, Sin, and Miſery.</p>
            <p>Is it not therefore worthy of our greateſt Application, and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to free our ſelves from ſo Dangerous Evils? Without doubt it is ſo. And this has always been the Care of the Wife: Preſent, as well as Future Happineſs, being concern'd in it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui Cupit aut metuit, juvat illum ſic Domus aut res;</l>
               <l>Ut Lippum pictae Tabulae fomenta podagram,</l>
               <l>Auriculas Citharae collecta ſorde dolentes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But we are to enquire what remedy Religion gives us to this Diſeaſe? And that we are ſure can be no other than Reaſon preſcribes; which is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59359:30"/>our Deſires to the worth of things: For where they go beyond that, we are certain to be diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whether we miſs, or obtain, what we deſire. But ſo far as the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things are in their real worth anſwerable to our Deſires; ſo far we are really Happy: And ſhould we always ſo ſucceed in a conſtant train of our Deſires, we ſhould, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Capacity, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Happy.</p>
            <p>We cannot conceive any Being to be without Deſires but God. Nor can we conceive it to be a fault for any Creature to act ſuitable to its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and deſire things that can be injoy'd; and will contribute to its Happineſs. This I am ſure Holy Writ allows us: For the Apoſtle tells us, That <hi>God has given us all things richly to injoy.</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, (whatever Metaphyſical Notions Mr. <hi>N.</hi> puts into him) tells the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Deut. xxvi. 11. <hi>Thou ſhalt rejoice in every good thing which the Lord thy God has given to thee; Thou
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59359:31"/>and the Levite, and the Stranger that is amongſt you:</hi> Which was but ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Land of Promiſe, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Milk, and Honey, propoſed to the Deſires of that whole People. And, I think, we may ſay, not one of the Six hundred Thouſand would have marched through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, had not <hi>Moſes</hi> allow'd them to deſire the good things of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but told them they muſt deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Creature. But our Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and Unhappineſs is, that we do not regulate our Deſires aright They are not under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Direction of our Reaſon, and Judgment; but lead theſe away Captive with them in their endleſs Chace after whatever ſtrikes our Imaginations with any Pleaſing Idea. The beſt Remedy for which that Reaſon can preſcribe, is what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion has injoyn'd us; <hi>viz.</hi> an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Love of God above all things. For our Deſires placed upon this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject will not only never be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; But alſo the Love of God
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59359:31"/>above all other things, will the moſt effectually ſecure us from any immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Love of any of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Becauſe the contrariety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch a Love of God, and any ſinful or inordinate Love of the Creature makes them inconſiſtent. If therefore the Love of God, and the Intereſts of another life, were conſtantly our Ruling and Predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Paſſion; If in this ſenſe (as low as it ſeems to Mr. <hi>N.</hi>) we did Love God <hi>with all our Heart, with all our Soul, and with all our Strength;</hi> We ſhould not only be ſecure of doing our Duty, but alſo make the beſt proviſion that we could for our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs even here in this World. For then the diſappointments we might meet with in the Love of any thing elſe, would never indanger the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of our Satisfaction; which, like a Houſe built upon a Rock, could not be mov'd by any Storms or Tempeſts of Fortune: And we might ſay, with Dr. <hi>H. More,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:59359:32"/>
               <q>
                  <l>What's Plague, or Priſon, Loſs of Friends,</l>
                  <l>War, Dearth, or Death, that all things Ends?</l>
                  <l>Mere Bugbears for the Childiſh Mind;</l>
                  <l>Pure Panick Terrors of the Blind.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which however it may look to ſome like a Religious Rant, is no more than in other inſtances we may find Experience to have made good the truth of. For even in the Love of the things of this World, very often, one Affection, or Deſire, has ſo much the Poſſeſſion of a Man's Heart, that all others (how natural a tendency ſoever he has to them) do but very weakly, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially affect him in their Succeſs, or Miſcarriage: And this no Man that is either very Ambitious; very Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous; very much in Love; or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd ſtrongly with any other Paſſion; can deny to be ſo.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59359:32"/>
            <p>The Love of God therefore as we are capable of loving him, (that is, chiefly, not ſolely) does effectually ſecure our Happineſs, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our Duty: For he deſires nothing of us, but that we ſhould be as Happy as he has made us capable of Being; And has laid no Traps, or Snares, to render us Miſerable; Nor does he require impoſſible Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances from us. Yet it is true nevertheleſs, that the conſtant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication that we have with ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Objects, which are apt too far to ingage our Affections, makes the Regulation of our Deſires to demand our greateſt Care, and Watchfulneſs: And too much can never be ſaid of the Neceſſity of this Duty, which in general conſiſts in deſiring every thing according to its worth: And the Objects of our Deſires are either Things of Temporal concern only, or of Eternal alſo; between which, as there cannot be in themſelves, ſo therefore there ought not to be in our Eſtimation, any Compariſon.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:59359:33"/>
            <p>Of things Temporal which are the Objects of our Deſires, They are either ſuch as are ſo, from Wants of Nature; or Wants of our own making. For it is certain, That Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and Education (to which we owe moſt of the Miſchiefs we ſuffer, and uſually charge upon Nature) have procur'd us very many Wants which She intended us not; And which therefore accordingly vary in different Countries, and Ages of the World: And theſe Wants are very many more (eſpecially in the Civiliz'd Nations as we call them) than the Wants of Nature; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Queis humana ſibi doleat</l>
                  <l>Natura negatis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>They are wiſe who indeavour to contract their Deſires to the laſt: But whoever ſays the Denial of what Nature requires, ought not to be eſteem'd an Unhappineſs, talks like a Diſciple of <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and not of Jeſus Chriſt; W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llowers are ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59359:33"/>often exhorted to do good to all Men: Which, at leaſt a chief part of it, conſiſts in removing the Pains and Miſeries they ſuffer from their Natural Wants, and Neceſſities: And This great part of Charity muſt be perform'd according to that Rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> xiii. 16. <hi>To do good and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch Sacrifice God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And altho' when the want of thoſe things which Nature requires, comes in competition with any good of Eternal Concernment, they may well be thought light, and be ſlighted in that Compariſon; yet in themſelves they cannot, nor ought to be ſo. And our Maſter himſelf, thought thus; When <hi>for the Joy that was ſet before him he indured the Croſs,</hi> &amp;c. But tho' it be a great part of Wiſdom to contract our Deſire, only to what Nature requires; Yet, as we muſt not ſeek the Satisfaction of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Appetites, when it cannot be obtain'd without prejudice to ſome
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59359:34"/>Duty which ought at that time to be preferr'd; So the gratification of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites which are not properly Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, but which we have receiv'd from Cuſtom, and Education, is not always Sinful. For beſides that Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom (which it may be was none of our fault) is oftentimes as ſtrong as Nature in us; Thoſe acquired Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites are alſo many times no ways prejudicial to what we owe either to God, or our Neighbour; And where they are not ſo, their Gratification cannot be Sinful. Our Saviour, who ſaid, <hi>This do, and thou ſhalt Live;</hi> aſſures us, That he who heartily loves God, and his Neighbour as himſelf, can make no miſtake in his Duty dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to his Salvation: And thoſe Miſtakes which are ſo, only to our happy living whilſt here; are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently puniſh'd in the diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they carry along with them. It is not therefore hard for a Man, if he be ſincere, to know when his Deſires are rightly regulated: And he will need no Caſuiſt beſides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59359:34"/>to tell him what, and how far, he may lawfully Love, or Deſire; and what or how far he may not do ſo. Loves he any thing in the World to the prejudice of his Love of God, or his Neighbour; it is Sinful: Does he not do ſo, there is no Sin. To oppoſe this, would be to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict thoſe words of our Saviour. And indeed theſe two great Duties of the Love of God, and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, imply or include each other. <hi>If,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, (1 <hi>John</hi> iv. 20.) <hi>a man ſay, I love God, and hateth his Brother, he is a Liar;</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and the Love of God is perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in us.</hi> Again, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Let us love one another, every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God:</hi> v. 8. <hi>He that loves not, knoweth not God:</hi> Chap. iii. 17. <hi>But who ſo has this Worlds Goods, and ſeeth his Brother have need, and ſhutteth up his Bowels of Compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the Love of God in him?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59359:35"/>
            <p>God is an inviſible Being: And it is by his Works, that we are led both to know, and to love him. They lead us to their inviſible Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. And if we lov'd not the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it is not conceiveable how we ſhould love God; at leaſt, how they ſhuld have lov'd him, who not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Law, yet did by Nature the things contain'd in the Law. And this, however oppoſite to what ſome tell us, ſeems nevertheleſs the ſenſe of the above-named Apoſtle, who ſays (1 <hi>John</hi> iv. 20.) <hi>He that loveth not his Brother whom he has ſeen, how can he love God whom he has not ſeen?</hi> And I would demand of any one if they could ſuppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or any other, never to have loved any Creature, what they could imagine they ſhould love? I ſuppoſe it muſt be reply'd by ſuch a one, That as he was not the Author of his own Being, and ſaw clearly that he could not be produced by nothing; He was thereby led to the Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Superiour Being, to whom
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59359:35"/>he was indebted for his own; and therefore ſtood obliged to love him. But <hi>Being,</hi> or <hi>Exiſtence,</hi> barely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, is ſo far from being a Good, that in the ſtate of the Damn'd, few are ſo Paradoxical as not to believe it an intolerable Miſery: And many, even in this World, are ſo unhappy, that they would much rather part with their Exiſtence, than be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally continued in the State they are in. The Author of our Being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore merits not our Love, unleſs he has given to us ſuch a Being as we can Love. Now if none of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that every way ſurround us, were pleaſing to us; How could our Beings, that have a continual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with, and neceſſary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon theſe, be ſo?</p>
            <p>But if the Objects that ſurround us do pleaſe us; that is, if we do love them; As it is then evident, they muſt be the firſt Objects of our Love, ſo from their Gratefulneſs, or Pleaſingneſs to us, it is alſo evident, that we have both the Idea of Love,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59359:36"/>and are led to the Diſcovery of the Author of that Being, that produces what is lovely. And like as our own Exiſtence, and that of other Beings, has aſſur'd us of the Exiſtence of ſome Cauſe more Powerful than theſe Effects; ſo alſo the Lovelineſs of his Works as well aſſures us, that that Cauſe, or Author, is yet more Lovely than they, and conſequently the Object the moſt worthy of our Love. But if none of thoſe Beings which ſurround us did move our Love, we ſhould then both be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Nature of the Author of all things, and of Love it ſelf. For what ſhould then exert it, that it ſhould not lie for ever Dormant? And which way could we (in the ſtate we are in) receive the Idea of Love, or Lovely? For God as Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful (which is all we ſhould know of him, conſider'd barely as a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator) is no more an Object of Love than of Hate, or Fear; and is truly an Object only of Admiration. It ſeems therefore plain, that if any
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59359:36"/>could be without the Love of the Creatures, they would be without the Love of God alſo: For as by the Exiſtence of the Creatures, we come to know there is a Creator; ſo by their Lovelineſs it is that we come to know That of their Author, and to Love him.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid here, That we have Pleaſing Senſations ('tis true) as ſoon as Perception; But that we have them not from the Beings which ſurround us, but from God. I ask, can we know this, before we know that there is a God? Or, will they ſay that we know there is a God as ſoon as ever we have Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception? Let it be true, that the Creatures have receiv'd no efficiency from God to excite pleaſing Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in us, and are but the occaſional Cauſes of thoſe we feel: Yet, does a Child in the Cradle know this? Or is this apparent ſo ſoon as it is that the Fire pleaſes us when we are Cold? or Meat when we are Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry? No, nor is it at any time a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59359:37"/>ſelf evident Truth. We muſt know many other Truths before we come to know this; which is a Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion containing many complex Ideas in it; and which we are not capable of framing, till we have been long acquainted with pleaſing Senſations. In the mean while, it is certain, that till we can make this Diſcovery, we ſhall neceſſarily Love that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to us to be the Cauſe of our Pleaſure, as much as if it really were ſo; It being unavoidably by us the ſame thing to us: And we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated by God himſelf to that which Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays is truly Idolatry. For our Paſſions are not moved by the reality, but appearance of things. To the prevention of which, this Notion were it true, and receiv'd amongſt Men as ſuch, could be of no uſe at all, neither could it teach them not to aſcend to the Love of God, by the Love of Creatures: Since it can be of uſe to none till they are convinc'd of it, and none are capable of being convinc'd of it,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59359:37"/>till ſenſible Objects by appearing the Cauſes of their Pleaſing Senſations, have gotten Poſſeſſion of their Love, and have as ſoon aſſur'd them that God is the Object the moſt worthy of their Love, as they have aſſured them of his Exiſtence. It is true, when firſt in our infancy we feel pleaſing Senſations, we are no more capable of being taught by them that there is a Superiour Inviſible Being that made theſe things to affect us thus, who therefore ought ſupreamly to be lov'd; than that this Inviſible Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at the Preſence of theſe Objects, exhibits to us a part of his own Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, by which theſe Pleaſing Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations are excited on occaſion of thoſe Objects without us, and that therefore he is only and ſolely to be loved. But tho' we are uncapable of theſe both alike, when firſt we cry for the Fire, or the Sucking-Bottle; Yet it is certain, that by the former way we are not only ſafe, all the time of our Ignorance, from the Sin of Idolatry, and the fatal pre-ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59359:38"/>of a ſinful affection; but that our love to God upon that ground is of eaſier deduction, and earlier ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended than by the latter. So ſoon as we do begin to leave off judging by appearances, and are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being convinc'd that the Diameter of the Sun exceeds that of a Buſhel; We are capable alſo of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that there is a Superiour Inviſible Being, the Author of thoſe things which afford us pleaſing Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, who therefore is ſupreamly to be loved. But if we are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſcaping Idolatry unleſs we love God alone, becauſe he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately exhibits to us a part of his Eſſence, by which all pleaſing Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations are caus'd in us, I fear all Mankind (before this preſent Age) lived and died Idolaters, and the greateſt part for the future will do ſo; Since I gueſs not One of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand will be found capable of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending, and being convinced of this new Hypotheſis of ſeeing all things in God. And as, I think, this cannot
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59359:38"/>be denied, ſo is it alſo more ſuitable to the Wiſdom, and Goodneſs of God, that it ſhould be true. For one muſt ſay, that the Happineſs and Welfare of Mankind were ill taken care for, if it depended upon a Knowledge, which not only few are ever likely to have, but which comes too late to any for much Uſe to be made of it. For when ſenſible Ideas have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Poſſeſſion of us for Twelve, or Twenty Years, they muſt be very ignorant of the conſtitution of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, that can think it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they ſhould preſently, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably they ſhould ever, be diſpoſſeſs'd by a Notion, altho' a true one.</p>
            <p>And for this, Mr. <hi>N.</hi> is not ſo kind as to furniſh us with any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. But he whom he is ſuppos'd to have receiv'd this Hypotheſis from, indeavours to ſolve the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Wiſdom of God in this Matter, and to help us out of this Difficulty, by making this Principle of our being obliged to have no Love for the Creatures, to be the very
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59359:39"/>Ground upon which Chriſtianity ſtands; Which he thus, in ſhort, accounts for.</p>
            <p>We muſt not Deſire, or Love the Creatures, they being uncapable to be our Good. We yet do Love, and deſire them, tho' Reaſon aſſures us of This. And our Doing thus, is the Original Sin which we bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World with us: Which makes us Children of Wrath, and liable to Damnation; Unable to pleaſe God but by a Mediator, both God and Man, who only could atone the Juſtice of God by the Excellency of his Sacrifice; Intercede to God by the Dignity of his Prieſthood; and ſend us the Holy Ghoſt by the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his Perſon.</p>
            <p>But as this Ground of Chriſtianity has a weak Foundation, <hi>viz.</hi> The Creature's being only occaſional Cauſes of our Pleaſing Senſations, (which is neither proved, nor would ſupport the Superſtructure that is rais'd upon it, if it could be proved) So it is to be hoped, that if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59359:39"/>what ſo few have receiv'd, or ſo much as thought of, we may yet be good Chriſtians. And thoſe ſeem more than a little to indanger Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, if not Deiſm alſo, who lay the great ſtreſs of their proof upon the Hypotheſis of ſeeing all things in God. For in that, the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for both (by which Atheiſts or Sceptics are propos'd to be brought over to Deiſm, or Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) terminates; in the <hi>Converſations Chreſtiennes</hi> of Mr. <hi>Malebranche,</hi> lately Tranſlated into Engliſh, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing amongſt us that <hi>Unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible way of Practical Religion,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſpoken of. And I doubt not, but if it were generally receiv'd and Preach'd by our Divines, that this Opinion of Seeing all things in God was the Baſis upon which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity was built, Scepticiſm would be ſo far from finding thereby a Cure, that it would ſpread it ſelf much farther amongſt us than it has yet done; And that many who find Chriſtianity a very Reaſonable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59359:40"/>in the Scriptures, would think it a very unaccountable one in a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem that (laying down That for its foundation) adds alſo further, That the Deſire we have to the Creature, is the Puniſhment of Sin, not the Inſtitution of Nature: For this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence is tranſmitted to us from our firſt Parent. <q>Qui voyoit claire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Dieu en toutes choſes: Il ſça<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voit avec evidence, que les Corps ne pouvoient eſtre ſon bien, ni le rendre par eux mêmes heureux ou Malheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reux en aucune maniére: Il eſtoit convaincu de l'opération continuelle de Dieu ſur luy; Mais ſa Conviction n'eſtoit pas ſenſible. Il le connoiſſoit ſans le ſentir. Au contraire il ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toit que les Corps agiſſoient ſur lui, quoy qu'il ne le connût pas. Il eſt vrai qu'eſtant raiſonnable, il devoit ſuivre ſa lumiére, et non pas ſon ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent; &amp; qu'il pouvoit facilement ſuivre ſa lumiére contre ſon ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſa connoiſance claire contre ſa ſenſation confuſe, parce qu'il arreſtoit ſans peine ſes ſentimens, lors-qu'il le
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59359:40"/>vouloit, à cauſe qu'il étoit ſans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence. Cependant s'arrêtant trop à ſes ſens, ſe laiſſant aller peu-à-peu à les écouter plus volontiers que Dieu même, à cauſe que les ſens parlent toûjours agréablement, et que Dieu ne le portoit pas à l'écouter par des plaiſirs prévenans qui au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roient diminué ſa Liberté; vous concevez bien comment il à pû s'é<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loigner de Dieu juſqu'à le perdre de vûe, pour s'unir de volonté à une Creatùre, <bibl>
                     <hi>Entr.</hi> iv. p. 106, 107.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>Who did clearly ſee God in all things, and evidently knew that Bodies could not be his true Good, nor properly make him in the leaſt happy, or unhappy, and was fully convinc'd of God's continual Operation on him. But he had no ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible conviction: He knew this, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling it. On the contrary, he could feel that Bodies acted on him, tho' he could not know it: Yet having Reaſon, he ſhould have follow'd his Light, not his Sentiment; And could have done it; ſince he could ſtop his Sentiment when he pleas'd, being free
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59359:41"/>from Concupiſcence: However defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to his ſenſes, and ſuffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to hearken to them more willingly than to God, by reaſon the ſenſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways move pleaſingly, and God did not move him by pre-ingageing Pleaſure, which might have leſſen'd his freedom, it is eaſie to conceive how he came to remove himſelf ſo far from God as to loſe ſight of him, and to joyn himſelf to the Creature.</hi> The ſame Author alſo gives us an account how <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity came to be infected; (which, it ſeems, was not from <hi>Adam,</hi> as is commonly taught, but from <hi>Eve</hi>) <q>à cauſe de l'union que les enfans ont avec leur mere, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 110.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>By reaſon of the Union that Children have with their Mother.</hi> 
               <q>Il n'y a point de fem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me qui n'ait dans le cerveau quelque trace &amp; quelque movement d'eſprits, qui la ſaſſe penſer, et qui la porte à quelque choſe de ſenſible. Or quand l'enfant eſt dans le ſein de ſa mere, il a les mêmes traces et les mêmes émotions d'eſprits que ſa mere; donc en cet état il connoît et aime les
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59359:41"/>corps, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 111.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>And there is no Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that has not ſome traces in her Brain, and motions of her Spirits, which carry her to ſomething ſenſible. Now when the Child is in the Womb of its Mother, it has the ſame traces, and the ſame motion of the Spirits: Therefore in this eſtate it knows and loves Bodies, and conſequently is born a Sinner.</hi> And this no holineſs of the Mother can hinder; Since <q>L'amour de Dieu ne ſe communique pas comme l'amour des Corps: Dont la raiſon eſt, que Dieu n'eſt pas ſenſible, et qu'il n'y a point de traces dans le Cerveau, qui par l'in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution de la Nature repreſentent Dieu, ni aucune des choſes qui ſont purement intelligibles.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Une femme peut bien ſe repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dieu ſous la forme d'un Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Vieillard: Mais lors qu'elle pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera à Dieu; son enfant penſera à un Vieillard: Lors qu'elle aimera Dieu, ſon enfant aura de l'amour pour les Vieillards, <bibl>
                     <hi>p.</hi> 112, 113.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>The Love of God does not communicate it
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59359:42"/>ſelf like the love of Bodies; Of which the reaſon is, that God is not ſenſible, and there are no Veſtiges in the Brain, which by the inſtitution of Nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent God, or anything that is purely intelligible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>So that the Children of Women who repreſent to themſelves God in the form of a Reverend old Man, will love Old Men: And whenever the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers think upon God and love God, the Children will think upon Old Men and love Old Men.</hi> Wherefore from this Original Corruption, ſprings the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Mediator, who muſt be both God and Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There ſeems to be ſome things in this Hypotheſis very unintelligible; And alſo that it has Conſequences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable to be admitted. But if neither of theſe were ſo; 'tis yet reaſon enough not to imbrace it, that it is no where either reveal'd, or prov'd; it being all but a Chain of Conſequences (ſuch as they are) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the Suppoſition of <hi>our ſeeing all things in God.</hi> For the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59359:42"/>we have to the Creatures, is aſſerted to be the Puniſhment of Sin, not the Inſtitution of Nature, becauſe (which is a ſtrange Reaſon) the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Creatures is ſuppos'd Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, upon the ground of their not being the Efficient Cauſes of our Pleaſing Senſations. And the Proof which is brought that they are not the Efficient Cauſes of our Pleaſing Senſations is, that we ſee all things in God. But this Proof it ſelf which is the Foundation of all, remains yet to be proved: For neither <hi>Pere Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branche,</hi> nor any one elſe has done it; nor I think can do it. And that which might alone give juſt ground for this Suſpicion is, That this Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis tends to the ſhaking and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettling the known Grounds of True Piety; tho' He, and a late Follower of his, would eſtabliſh it upon this new, and formerly unknown Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p>But ſetting aſide thoſe Abſurdities that this new Conceit would run us into, in Morality (which are ſufficient
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59359:43"/>Reaſons for rejecting it) there are, I doubt not, ſome, who, if they would be at the Pains to treat it Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically, might be able to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate its Weakneſs and Inconſiſtency on other Grounds, as well as thoſe of Morality. But whether, or no, any one ſhall believe That a Work worth their while; This Hypotheſis ſeems, yet at leaſt, of moment enough to be ſo far inquired into, as theſe Papers have Undertaken: Since how unſerviceable or injurious ſoever it really is to Piety, it has yet been Seriouſly and Zealouſly pretended to be of great Uſe to Religion; And that not only by a young Writer, whoſe Judgment may, perhaps, be thought By aſſed by the Affectation of Novelty; But alſo it is made the very Ground of Chriſtianity, by a Man of an eſtabliſh'd Character in the World for Philoſophical Science. But as Chriſtianity (whatever ſome are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded) is a rational Religion, and needs no Inventions of Men to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it; ſo it receives no Advantage
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59359:43"/>by this, which it has not in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, and commonly receiv'd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Original Sin. That ſerves to all the purpoſes this is brought in for, as well; and therefore makes this Needleſs; Unleſs it be pretended that the Opinion of Seeing all things in God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is needful to give Light to, and to make the commonly receiv'd Doctrine of Original Sin intelligible; Which is, to charge this Doctrine with having wanted ſuch Evidence before this Diſcovery was made, as was neceſſary for the making it the Foundation of Chriſtian Religion: Which ſurely thoſe cannot agree to who have made it ſo. And thoſe who have not made it ſo, will not be concern'd in the Light pretended to be brought to it; The thing it ſelf being no more prov'd by this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of the manner of it, than it was before. Upon which of theſe two accounts, or whatever other, Mr. <hi>N.</hi> declin'd, or approv'd not the declaring this Opinion of the Creatures not being Efficient Cauſes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59359:44"/>of our Senſations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be the Ground and Baſis of Chriſtianity; Yet certainly his Subject (eſpecially being Preached to a Country Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation) obliged him, if not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the Goodneſs of God in this Matter, in making us without any fault of ours, the Subjects of his Wrath; yet at leaſt to have ſhow'd which way we were to be brought out of that State, and by what means after we were come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, we ſhould be made obedient to it. For if (as it is to be hoped he does) he believes God to wink at our Sins in the time of our Ignorance, before we are capable of underſtanding the Creatures to be only Occaſional Cauſes of our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Senſations; Yet we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe when Men are convinced of that Truth, they are call'd on not only to Repentance, but Amendment. And if Loving the Creatures ſo, as yet to be willing readily to part with them all for the Love of God, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than offend in any thing that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59359:44"/>we know to be our Duty, (which is the higheſt Love of him that moſt People can conceive themſelves ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of,) will not hinder us from being truely Idolaters, and Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious; Whilſt being Hungry or Cold, Food or Fire are deſired by us; And that we cannot Love our Children, or Friends, without looking on them as Goods Deſireable to us; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks he ſhould tell us by what means we may get rid of Appetites and Affections ſo offenſive to God, and deſtructive to our Soul's Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and ſhould let us know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he finds this attainable by our own Natural Abilities, or whether Chriſt has Purchas'd the Ability of doing it for thoſe that believe in him; Or what we are to do, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of our ſelves in an Eſtate ſo deplorable. He ſays indeed, <hi>That could we but ſee how God alone acts in us, and Cauſes all our Senſations, whilſt the Creatures ſtand mute and ſilent, like ſo many Ciphers in his Preſence, having not the leaſt Activity or Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59359:45"/>upon us; We ſhould quickly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs the whole Creation from our Hearts, and be wholly ſwallow'd up by the Love of God.</hi> But as the caſe is, he gives us no Remedy at all. For his making <hi>no queſtion</hi> afterwards, <hi>but that it is thus in Heaven, and that this is the Meaſure of Divine Love There,</hi> is ſo far from helping us; That it will not ſo much as infer (if he could prove it were ſo) that this ought to be the Meaſure of Divine Love upon Earth. But we have a better Authority than his for it, That we know not what we ſhall be There; Therefore cannot tell what may be added to, or chang'd in our preſent Faculties: And as for thoſe of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Arch-Angels, (which he mentions) we are yet leſs acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them: And every one will not be convinc'd (tho' they did agree in Mr. <hi>N</hi>—'s Suppoſition concerning them) that it were more reaſonable to propoſe or pray to be like them (at leaſt whilſt upon Earth) then it would be for the Fiſhes (if they were
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59359:45"/>capable of it) to propoſe, or pray to God, that they might fly in the Air like Birds; or Ride Poſt-Horſes as Men do. For it may be our Earthly Element no more admits of the firſt, than theirs of the laſt. And thoſe muſt be very little conſiderate or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in their Prayers, who will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ask God for their ſakes, to change the Order of Nature, which he has eſtabliſh'd. It is certain, that if we had no Deſires but after God, the ſeveral Societies of Mankind could not long hold together, nor the very Species be continued: For few would give themſelves Care, and Sorrow, in the purſuit of Poſſeſſions not deſireable.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>N.</hi> pretends that there are places of Scripture, beſides that of his Text, which make good his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Scripture-Authority, is that to which Reaſon may ſafely refer it ſelf: But it were to be wiſhed that it were appeal'd to with more Care and Conſideration than it often is; and that Men would not preſently,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59359:46"/>becauſe perhaps they are perſwaded their Opinions are Right, back them with any Text of Scripture that they can make Chime to them, tho' they be very little, or not at all to the Purpoſe; as they could not often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times but diſcern, if they would but either regard the Scope of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; or read to the end of it.</p>
            <p>The firſt Text Mr. <hi>N.</hi> brings for his purpoſe, is <hi>Mat.</hi> vi. 24. <hi>No Man can ſerve two Maſters; for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or elſe he will hold to the one, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the other; ye cannot ſerve God and Mammon.</hi> Here, Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays, <hi>We are plainly told, we cannot divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God, and the Creature: and the reaſon is not only becauſe our Capacities are too narrow and ſcanty to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd upon two ſuch vaſtly different Objects; but alſo becauſe we cannot love either of them, but upon ſuch a Principle as muſt utterly exclude the Love of the other. For we muſt not love any thing but what is our true Good, what can both deſerve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59359:46"/>our Love: And there can be but one thing that is ſo, and that muſt either be God or the Creature. If then the Creature be our Good, let us Love That, and that only; That, and not God: But if God be our True Good (as moſt certainly he is) then let us Love God, and God only; God, and not the Creature: For 'tis a moſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent and impracticable thing to talk of Carving out our Love between both: Ye cannot ſerve God and Mammon.</hi> Practical Diſcourſe, <hi>p.</hi> 64, 65. By <hi>Mammon,</hi> I ſuppoſe was never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood before, any thing but Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or thoſe things for which Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are deſired: And our Saviour here tells us, we muſt not ſet our Hearts upon theſe things, or make our ſelves Slaves, or Servants to them: That is, the Deſire of them muſt not command us; If we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it, and make it Obedient to Reaſon, it is then certain it does not command us, and conſequently that we are not Servants to it. This is then plainly no more, but that our
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59359:47"/>Deſires after Riches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt not be beyond their Worth; So as that we forget they are periſhable, and uncertain Goods, ſuch as Moth and Ruſt do corrupt, and the Violence and Injuſtice of Men may deprive us of; No longer (at beſt) of any value, than during our ſhort abode in this World. For, if we do otherwiſe, our Reaſon is captivated, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come truly Servants; The Servants of Mammon; And cannot be the Servants of God; Becauſe we cannot Serve two ſo oppoſite and differing Maſters. For it is from the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of their Commands, and not from the littleneſs of our Minds, or Capacities, that we cannot Serve God and Mammon; Since neither little nor great can obey two Maſters that command Contraries; And that is true of the Apoſtle, <hi>His Servants ye are, to whom you obey.</hi> But our Minds, as little as they are, may love God, and the Creature; when the Love of the Creature is Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate; And I think Mr. <hi>N.</hi> nor no
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59359:47"/>one elſe, will deny, That there are many who ſincerely love God, that do yet love ſomething in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; And if ſo, whether their Love be Sinful, or no, it is evident their Capacities are not too little to love both; As it is alſo that our Reaſon is not captivated, and we thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlav'd, or render'd the Servants of every thing that we love. And here is nothing at all ſaid by our Saviour of any other degree of Love, but ſuch as makes us the Servants of what we love. And therefore it is no more true that we are here forbid by our Saviour to love any thing but God, than that our Capacities are too little to love any two different Objects. For if Mr. <hi>N.</hi> means any thing elſe by <hi>to be employ'd,</hi> than To Love, when he ſays, <hi>That our Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities are too narrow and ſcanty to be employ'd upon two ſuch vaſtly different Objects,</hi> it is not to his purpoſe. But if he means by <hi>employ'd,</hi> to Love; what he affirms is then neither true in his own ſence of Love, nor in that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59359:48"/>of the Text. For it is not true that our Capacities are too narrow to Love any two different Objects, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſmalleſt degree, (which he contends for) or ſo as to become the Servants of them, which is what the Text ſays; Provided, there be no contrariety in their Commands. His firſt Reaſon therefore why we cannot divide our Love, <hi>viz.</hi> From the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of Our Capacities, is utterly falſe; our Capacities being evidently not too narrow to love any two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Objects, or even every Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject which appears to us to be love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And there is no reaſon that if we love the Creatures in ſome degree, as occaſions of Pleaſure to us (we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily loving whatever is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Pleaſure) that That Love of the Creature ſhould exclude the Love of God; any more than that the Love of Cherries ſhould exclude the love of our Friend that gives them us. And if we love God, yet leſs does the Love of him exclude our Love of his Creatures: For we love
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59359:48"/>them then not only for the Pleaſure that they occaſion us, but for the ſake of their Author; and the more we Love God, the more we ſhall Love his Creatures.</p>
            <p>But another Reaſon, beſides the narrowneſs of our Capacities, Why <hi>we cannot divide our Love</hi> between God and the Creature, is, <hi>becauſe we cannot love either of them, but upon ſuch a Principle as muſt utterly exclude the love of the other;</hi> which is thus offer'd to be made out: <hi>We muſt not love any thing but what is our true Good: There can be but one thing that is ſo: And that muſt be either God, or the Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is our <hi>True Good,</hi> he tells us is that which can both <hi>Deſerve and Reward our Love.</hi> But certainly whatever is a Good to us, is a <hi>True Good;</hi> ſince whatever pleaſes us, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes us: And our Love, which he ſays is to be <hi>deſerv'd and rewarded,</hi> is nothing elſe but that Diſpoſition of Mind, which we find in our ſelves towards any thing with which we are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59359:49"/>pleas'd. So that to tell us, that we muſt not love any thing but what is our <hi>True God;</hi> Is as much as to ſay, that we muſt not be pleas'd with any thing but what Pleaſes us; which it is likely we are not in Danger of. And what is added of <hi>deſerving and rewarding our Love,</hi> being put in as a Synonymous Expreſſion, to explain to us what is meant by our <hi>True Good;</hi> Our <hi>True Good,</hi> does conſequently tell us what is meant by <hi>deſerving and rewarding our Love;</hi> They both ſignifying one and the ſame thing. There can therefore no more be made of This notable Principle, <hi>viz. That we muſt not love any thing but what is our True Good,</hi> that is, <hi>which can both deſerve and reward our Love,</hi> then that we muſt not be pleaſed with any thing but what Pleaſes us; or reflect upon the Pleaſure any thing cauſes in us, which never did cauſe us any Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>This, without doubt, carries much information with it; But the word <hi>True</hi> (otherwiſe very impertinent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59359:49"/>here) is Subtilty to inſinuate that which ſhould be prov'd, <hi>viz. That the Creatures are not the Eſſicient Cauſes</hi> of our Pleaſing Senſations. And in the Lines following, he ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples not to beg the Queſtion in more expreſs terms; When he ſays, <hi>There can be but one thing that is ſo; viz.</hi> our <hi>True Good:</hi> And then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>and that muſt be either God, or the Creature; But if God be our True Good (as moſt certainly he is) let us Love God, and God only; God and not the Creature: For 'tis a moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent and impracticable thing to carve out our Love between both: Ye cannot ſerve God, and Mammon.</hi> Here we ſee, having needleſly told us that we <hi>muſt not love any thing but our True Good;</hi> That is, that which pleaſes us; He tells us next, that there can be but one thing that is ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> our <hi>True Good:</hi> Which is yet more evidently falſe, than his firſt Aſſertion is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent. Notwithſtanding, as if it were as evidently True, as it is manifeſtly the contrary; He offers
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59359:50"/>not any thing at all to make it good; His Aſſertion only ſeeming to him ſufficient to oppoſe to the daily Senſe and Experience of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. But indeed if by <hi>True Good,</hi> he did mean our chief Good; then it is true that there is but one ſuch Good, and that is God alone, who is alſo the Author and Donor of all our other Good: But in this ſenſe it is nothing to his purpoſe. To conclude his Demonſtration, <hi>that we cannot Love God, or the Creature, but upon ſuch a Principle as muſt ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly exclude the Love of the other;</hi> Having ſaid we <hi>muſt Love nothing but our True Good;</hi> and <hi>that That can be but one thing;</hi> He tells us laſtly, that that one thing <hi>muſt be either God or the Creature.</hi> Which Concluſion, when he has prov'd his foregoing Aſſertion, <hi>viz. That there can be but one thing our Good;</hi> it may be convenient for him to explain a little better; But till he has proved that there is but one thing a Good to us, this laſt Aſſertion ſerves for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59359:50"/>nothing, unleſs to make it more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he has all along ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Purpoſe. For his Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <hi>that we cannot Love either God, or the Creature, but upon ſuch a Principle as muſt utterly exclude the Love of the other,</hi> Was of as much Authority to us as his Aſſertion, <hi>that there can be but one thing a Good to us:</hi> And there is no more proof offer'd by him for the one, than the other.</p>
            <p>This, I believe, his own Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Experience, has often offer'd to him, for the confutation of what he affirms, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is not true that all Men in the World either Love God, and God only; Or the Creature only, and God not at all: Which ought to be, according to his Principles. But the Admonition of St. <hi>John,</hi> he ſays, is ſomewhat more expreſs to his Purpoſe than that of our Saviour was, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Love not the World nor the things of the World: If any Man love the World, the Love of the Father is not
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59359:51"/>in him.</hi> Here again Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, that according to the common Interpretation, <hi>this is meant of the immoderate love of the World.</hi> But he ſays, <hi>they interpreted it ſo for want of Principles on which to raiſe a higher ſenſe. 'Tis plain the words import more;</hi> viz. <hi>That we are not to love the World at all; That all Love of it is immoderate.</hi> And by his, former meaſures (before laid down) it appears how, and why, it is ſo. But I believe St. <hi>John</hi> will be found to explain himſelf much better than Mr. <hi>N.</hi> explains him. St. <hi>John</hi> ſays, <hi>Love not the World, nor the things of the World; If any Man love the World, the Love of the Father is not in him.</hi> Now the Queſtion is, whether Mr. <hi>N.</hi> be in the right in underſtanding (as he does) by <hi>Love;</hi> every the leaſt degree of Love: Or whether other Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſo, in thinking that by <hi>Love,</hi> immoderate Love is meant: And I think there needs nothing more to ſatisfie us that the laſt are in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59359:51"/>Right than Mr. <hi>N—</hi>'s own conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That without his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, this Scripture could not be underſtood otherwiſe than thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters underſtand it: So that unleſs St. <hi>John</hi> writ not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by thoſe he wrote to; or that the Chriſtians to whom he wrote, had Mr. <hi>N—</hi>'s Hypotheſis, it is paſt doubt that the other Interpreters he mentions are to be thought in the Right. But becauſe it is believed by him, that St. <hi>John,</hi> who ſo much preſſes Love to others, had himſelf ſo little Love to Mankind, as to leave the ſtrongeſt inforcement of their greateſt Duty in obſcurity; We will ſee whether, or no, there is any appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that he did ſo; And whether Mr. <hi>N-</hi>'s Hypotheſis ſerve to illuſtrate this Scripture. For that this Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis could not be learnt from it, is apparently confeſs'd; Becauſe the Hypotheſis muſt be known (as he himſelf owns) before the Scripture Proof of it can be underſtood: And therefore our former Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59359:52"/>this Hypotheſis from the Goodneſs, and Wiſdom of God, that would not permit a Doctrine of the conſequence this is pretended to be, to be ſo obſcure as it is, ſtands ſtill good, for all this freſh pretence to Scripture Proof. But St. <hi>John</hi> (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.15.) ſays, <hi>Love not the World, nor the things which are in the World: If any Man love the World, the Love of the Father is not in him.</hi> Now that this is meant of the ſinful Pleaſures of the World, or the immoderate, and conſequently ſinful Love of Pleaſures in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not ſinful; what words can make Plainer than the immediately following ones, wherein the Reaſons are given why we ſhould not Love, the World, nor the things of the World? <hi>viz.</hi> (<hi>v.</hi> 16.) Becauſe all that is in the World, as <hi>the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life, is not of the Father, but is of the World:</hi> That is, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not from God, but from the Paſſions, Vanities, and Follies of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59359:52"/>and ſinful Men: And we ſhould not ſet our Hearts upon the World; That is, even the allowable Pleaſures of it; Becauſe (<hi>v.</hi> 17.) <hi>The World paſſes away;</hi> And therefore by no means ought to be conſider'd as the ultimate Good of a Being of a more induring Nature; But is indeed ſo far remov'd from it, as the little Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the one holds of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the endleſs Duration of the other. This is what St. <hi>John</hi> ſays; And it ſeems too plain to need any other Explanation, than what he himſelf has given. But as if every Text in Scripture were a diſtinct Aphoriſm, it is frequently enough quoted by ſome, without any regard to what goes before, or to what comes after; with how much ſincerity cannot be ſaid; But certainly to the manifeſt bringing into Contempt thoſe Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Truth.</p>
            <p>But for whatever Cauſe Mr. <hi>N.</hi> omitted theſe Reaſons of St. <hi>John</hi> for our <hi>not loving the World, and the things of it;</hi> And ſubſtitured one of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59359:53"/>his own in the Place; <hi>viz. That the Creatures are not the Efficient, but Occaſional Cauſe of our Pleaſing Senſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> He does ſay, That, without the knowledge of this his Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, we cannot know that every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Love of the Creature is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and conſequently that St. <hi>John</hi>'s Reaſons for inforcing the Duty he urges, were defective. But St. <hi>John</hi> tells us not that every degree of Love of the Creature is ſinful: On the contrary, he ſays, <hi>If we love not our Brother whom we have ſeen, how can we love God whom we have not ſeen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore there is no more need of Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s Opinion, to inforce what St. <hi>John</hi> teaches; than there is uſe of what St. <hi>John</hi> teaches to confirm Mr. <hi>N—</hi>'s Opinion. For that St. <hi>John</hi> meant not by Love every degree of Love, is evident; Both becauſe he would contradict himſelf if he did, and alſo from the Reaſons he gives why we ſhould not love the World, and the things of the World: <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:59359:53"/>Becauſe all that is in the World <hi>is not of the Father, and paſſes away</hi> quickly. For he would either have given us the true Reaſon of This, or ſtopping where Mr. <hi>N.</hi> did in his Citation of him, not have miſled us, by giving us Reaſons, which not only reach not the matter, But which alſo ſerve to Determine us to another ſenſe. For, as ſhort-liv'd Flowers, tho' they ought not to imploy the continual care of our whole lives, may yet reaſonably enough be found in our Gardens, and delight us in their Seaſons; So the fading Good Things of this Life, tho' (for that reaſon) they are not to be fixed on as the Ultimate Good of Eternal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yet there is no reaſon why we may not rejoice in them, as the good Gifts of God, and find all that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light which he has joined with the lawful uſe of them.</p>
            <p>But St. <hi>John</hi> ſays, <hi>Love not;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays, we muſt <hi>not Love them at all.</hi> Our Saviour alſo in St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> in the Chapter above
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59359:54"/>cited, ſays, <hi>Seek not:</hi> But Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays not in like manner <hi>ſeek not at all.</hi> On the contrary, he tells us very expreſly, we may ſeek the good things of this World, provided we love them not. Now, if he knows a Reaſon why one of theſe places muſt be taken ſtrictly according to the Letter, and not the other; he was doubtleſs obliged to tell it us; eſpecially having been ſo indulgent to Seeking as to have given no rules of reſtriction to that. But our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſays, <hi>Seek not what ye ſhall Eat, or what ye ſhall Drink, or with what you ſhall be cloathed, for after theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek.</hi> Mr. <hi>N.</hi> muſt doubtleſs ſay to this that our Saviour meant by not ſeeking, that we ſhould not ſeek immoderately, and ſolicitouſly; And ſo ſay others to what St. <hi>John</hi> ſays: The ſenſe of the Diſcourſe in both places deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining that to be the meaning of both. And till Mr. <hi>N.</hi> has told us why <hi>Seeking</hi> muſt be underſtood in this ſenſe, and not <hi>Loving</hi> be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59359:54"/>ſo; he cannot ſurely diſallow of it, if (after his example) we thus underſtand the words of St. <hi>John,</hi> viz. That we ſhould not love immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately; that is, beyond the worth of what we love. And thus the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of St. <hi>John</hi> is no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to his purpoſe than that of our Saviour, in St. <hi>Matt.</hi> was. I am ſure the reaſon with which St. <hi>John</hi> inforces his Admonition, is expreſly contrary to that with which Mr. <hi>N.</hi> inforces his interpretation of it. St. <hi>John</hi> ſays, <hi>Love not the World,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For all that is in the World,</hi> viz. <hi>the luſt of the Fleſh, the luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life, is not of the Father, but is of the World.</hi> But Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays, Love not the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For all that is in the World, <hi>viz.</hi> all thoſe Pleaſures Worldly-minded Men ſo greedily hunt after; as <hi>the luſt of the Fleſh, the luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life,</hi> are not of the World, but of the Fathe: Which ſeems not only to oppoſe St. <hi>John;</hi> But alſo ſounds very harſhly, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59359:55"/>offenſively to many Pious Perſons; Who are apt to think it unworthy of, and miſ-becoming the Majeſty of the great God, <hi>who is of Purer Eyes than to behold iniquity,</hi> to be as it were at the beck of his ſinful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to excite in them Sentiments of Delight, and Pleaſure, whenever they are diſpos'd to tranſgreſs againſt his Laws, tho' in the moſt groſs, and erroneous Inſtances.</p>
            <p>But the Author of this Hypotheſis tells us, That this is that indeed which makes Sin to be ſo exceeding ſinful, <hi>viz.</hi> That we oblige God in Virtue of that firſt immutable Law, or Order, which he has eſtabliſh'd (that is, of exciting Sentiments of Pleaſure in us upon ſome opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bodies upon us) to Reward our Tranſgreſſions againſt him with Pleaſure, and Delight. It is ſtrange that we cannot ſeem ſinful enough, without having a Power of forcing God to be a Partner in our Wickedneſs! But this is a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of an Hypotheſis whoſe uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59359:55"/>and want of proof, are alone ſufficient Cauſes for rejecting it. And if we will once quit what Reaſon and Revelation evidently and plainly tell us, to build our Religion upon the foundation of uncertain Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; where muſt we ſtop? Every Man, indeed, cannot ſo handſomly compoſe his Syſtem as <hi>P. Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branche;</hi> But every Man has as much Authority to impoſe it upon others, or to be credited without Proof. The abovemention'd account of Sin, is plainly only ſupported upon its being a conſequence of our ſeeing all things in God; who being the alone efficient Cauſe of all our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Senſations, muſt neceſſarily be the only efficient Cauſe of ſinful, as well as innocent Pleaſures: But no Pleaſure, ſimply as Pleaſure, being evil, God is not ſuppos'd in this by <hi>P. Malebranche</hi> the Author of Sin, but only Man himſelf; Who, he ſays, <q>étant pecheur &amp; par conſequent indigne d'être récompenſé par des ſentimens agréables, oblige Dieu
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59359:56"/>en conſéquence de ſes volontés im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muables, de luy faire ſentir du plaiſir dans le tems même qu'il l'offenſe. <bibl>Entr. III. p. 91.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <hi>We being Sinners, and by conſequence unworthy to be recompenc'd by agreeable Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, oblige God in conſequence of his immutable Will, to make us feel plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the time that we offend him. Viz.</hi> Whenever we Love or Delight in any Creature. But our ſeeing all things in God, upon which this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sin, of Original Corruption, and the following account of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity ſtands, remains yet to be better proved; Before we reject, for ſo unintelligible a fancy, what is evident and plain; What may ſatisfie the Wife, and what the Weak (whoſe Souls are Doubtleſs of as much value, and They as much concern'd for them) may eaſily comprehend.</p>
            <p>That God has made us Reaſonable Creatures, we certainly know: And it is evident alſo, that by virtue of our being ſuch; we are obliged to Live by the Law of Reaſon; which
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59359:56"/>whenever we tranſgreſs, we muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily offend againſt God; We in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting that Order which he has eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, in making that to obey, which ought to command; and that to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which ought to obey. And that we are ſo prone (as Experience ſhews we are) to offend againſt this Law of Reaſon, is from the Unrulineſs of our Affections; Which being ſtrong in us, (whilſt Reaſon is weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to direct them) take up with the firſt alluring Objects, whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions making ſettled habits in us, it is not eaſie for Reaſon to remove them, even when it does diſcover their Pravity; and ſets us to ſtruggle againſt them. And to this looſe Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and ill Cuſtom, greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute: There being ſcarce any Vice we are capable of, which is not inſtill'd into us (or at leaſt the Seeds of it) in our very Childhood, by thoſe fooliſh People that uſually have the Direction of it. For it is obvious that there are few Children who are not taught by their Nurſes to be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59359:57"/>Proud, Angry, Covetous, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful; and principled with thoſe Vices, even before they have Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage enough to talk of them. But God made <hi>Adam</hi> a Man, and not a Child; Therefore his Reaſon was in its full ſtrength as early as his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites; and he had not the unhappy Preventions which others receive. He himſelf therefore, and his Poſterity, one would have thought, ran no very great Hazard of loſing thoſe Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages his Obedience would have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured them.</p>
            <p>That Mankind did loſe by <hi>Adam</hi> what they are reſtor'd to by Jeſus Chriſt, we are plainly told in the Scripture: But that by his Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or <hi>Eve</hi>'s, any one ſingle Soul ſhould be doom'd to Eternal Miſery, or to any condition worſe than not being; whether immediately, as ſome hold, for <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin; or by ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them to a ſtate of neceſſary ſinning; Can neither comport with the Goodneſs of God, or is any where reveal'd in Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:59359:57"/>
            <p>The laſt of theſe Opinions, <hi>Pere Malebranche</hi>'s Hypotheſis maintains; tho' he accounts for it differently from others. Children, he expreſly tells us, become (through their Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with their Mothers) Sinners; and are in a ſtate of Damnation before they are born into the World. But both the Apoſtle and Reaſon aſſure us, that where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion. And <hi>Pere Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branche</hi> oppoſes this, upon no other ground offer'd by him for ſo doing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that the concluſion he makes, <hi>viz.</hi> That Children are born Sinners, is a neceſſary conſequence of our ſeeing all things in God. For God only cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing us Pleaſure, he only has a right to our Love, and all love of the Creature is ſinful. But <hi>a Child (by virtue of its union with the Mother) does, whilſt in her Womb, know and love Bodies; conſequently therefore is a Sinner, and ſhall be neceſſarily Damn'd,</hi> p. 114. (Tho' indeed in a Note upon that Word, he mitigates the ſenſe of it to being eternally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59359:58"/>of the Poſſeſſion of God). And that we come into the World utterly uncapable to pleaſe God, (as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſays we do) is not through any fault at all of our own, but for <hi>Eve</hi>'s; Concerning whoſe Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion any ways influencing her Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, the Scripture yet makes no mention at all.</p>
            <p>However, this Principle is made by <hi>Pere Malebranthe</hi> (p. 94.) the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Chriſtianity. But it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the New Teſtament tells us nothing of it: And there it is, ſurely, that we ought to look for the Chriſtian Religion. What we are there told, is, That <hi>as in Adam all died, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live,</hi> 1 Cor. xv. 22. <hi>That he came to aboliſh Death, and to bring Life and Immortality to light,</hi> 2 Tim. i. 10. <hi>That we ſhall be juſtified by Faith, without the works of the Law,</hi> Rom. iii. 28. And that for this end, <hi>God ſent his Son into the World, that as many as believe in him might have Eternal Life.</hi> Yet <hi>do we then</hi> (ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle)
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59359:58"/>
               <hi>make void the Law through Faith? God forbid! yea, we eſtabliſh the Law.</hi> Rom. iii. 31. But the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God in Chriſt Jeſus, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in this, that we are hereby at once the moſt effectually put upon uſing our Endeavours to <hi>work out our Salvation with fear and trembling;</hi> And alſo kept from Deſpair, in the ſenſe of our own weakneſs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that Law which <hi>Adam</hi> in his more Advantageous Circumſtances tranſgreſſing againſt, forfeited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Bliſs and Immortality: We ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not only a Promiſe that we ſhall receive from God whatever (asking as we ought) we ſhall ask in his Son's Name; And alſo of his Spirit to help our Infirmities; But to compleat all, that for the ſake of Chriſt, our ſincere, tho' imperfect. Obedience ſhall be accepted; Faith in him ſupplying its defects.</p>
            <p>This is what the Scripture tells us of the Diſpenſation of God to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the Goſpel of his Son: Which is ſo viſibly ſuitable to, and worthy
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59359:59"/>of the Divine Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that no Inventions of Man can add any thing to it, to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more ſo. yet were our Views larger than to comprehend only the compaſs of our little Globe, they would probably afford us ſtill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Matter for our Admiration. For 'tis a thought too limitted and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for Women and Children now to be kept in, that this Spot of ours is all the Habitable part of the Creation. But without underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Syſtem of the World, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what Mathematicians and Naturaliſts offer to convince us, that ſo many Regions fit for Inhabitants are not empty Deſarts, and ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs Orbs of Light more inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant than ſo many Farthing Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles; We read, in the Scripture, of other Ranks of Intelligent Beings, beſides our ſelves; Of whom, tho' it would be Preſumption to affirm any thing beyond what is reveal'd, yet we know not what Relation may poſſibly be between them and us.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59359:59"/>The Scripture plainly intimates great Numbers of them, Superiour to us in the Dignity of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be fallen by Diſobedience (like Man) from a Happier State; And alſo that they are Enemies to us: Whether out of Envy for what Jeſus Chriſt had undertaken for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, or for other Reaſons, we know not. But by the ſmall account we have of them, they ſeem to have ſet up themſelves in oppoſition to their Maker, as thinking themſelves ſufficient to carve out their own Happineſs; And ſhall find full reward of their Folly and Rebellion, when the Judgment of the great Day ſhall meet them.</p>
            <p>But on Man, who after his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion ſaw his Nakedneſs, and was aſham'd, the Father of Mercies has had Compaſſion, and has found out a Way for his Reſtoration: Such a Way as may well <hi>humble theſe Proud ones in the Imagination of their hearts;</hi> And which leaves no room to us for Boaſting. For it is certain, That <hi>by
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59359:60"/>the Works of the Law no Fleſh ſhall be Juſtified,</hi> Rom. iii. 20. Faith, which would have preſerved <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocence, ſhall alone juſtifie his Poſterity. And tho' the Wiſdom of God has made Faith in his Son that which is required to Salvation, in thoſe to whom he is reveal'd; We are told that <hi>the Juſt,</hi> in all Ages, have <hi>liv'd by Faith:</hi> Which is neceſſarily the Immutable Baſis of all true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For without we believe not only in the Being, but alſo in the Veracity of God, <hi>That he Is, and that he is a Rewarder of them that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſeek him,</hi> it is impoſſible we ſhould love <hi>him with all our Hearts, with all our Souls,</hi> &amp;c. which contains the whole Moral Law; Whoſe Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations not being Arbitrary, but ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the Nature of things, muſt neceſſarily under every Diſpenſation be always the ſame: And Chriſt tells us expreſly, <hi>He came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this Law, but to fulfil it.</hi> He came to give us a clearer and fairer Tranſcript of it; To inforce it by his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59359:60"/>Authority and Example; To aſſure us of our own Future Exiſtence, which Reaſon could not; And of the great Love of God to Mankind, in accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Faith to ſupply the Defects of Sincere Obedience; By which we are freed from the Terrours of an offended Deity; And have hopes of being made Heirs of a glad Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; Co-heirs with Chriſt, the Author and Finiſher of our Salvation, Who, for the Joy that was ſet before him, indured the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame, and has obtain'd for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Kingdom of which all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are the Subjects. We are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored by him to a more aſſured Felicity than that from which <hi>Adam</hi> fell, by not believing that <hi>in the Day he ate of the forbidden Fruit he ſhould ſurely Die;</hi> Too little attending to the Light of his Reaſon; (Which would have taught him not to queſtion the Divine Veracity) and having yet no Experience to oppoſe to the Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his Appetite. And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps God in this Reſtoration of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59359:61"/>by Jeſus Chriſt <hi>(who took not on him the Nature of Angels)</hi> having herein <hi>put down the Mighty from their feats, and exalted thoſe of Low degree,</hi> does by this Oeconomy of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in our Salvation, teach <hi>all</hi> the Orders of Intellectual Beings, whom he has made free Agents (as well as Man) That as he cannot make a Being Independent on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for its Happineſs; So the moſt inlightned Reaſon is only ſafe and ſecure, whilſt it feels its weakneſs and dependency: Which if we be thoroughy, as we ought, ſenſible of, we ſhall neceſſarily <hi>love God with all our Hearts, with all our Souls,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays theſe words ſignifie, <hi>That we muſt love nothing but God alone.</hi> And to confirm that his ſenſe of them, he brings yet two other places of Scripture: The firſt is, <hi>james</hi> iv. 4. <hi>Ye Adulterers and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſes, know ye not that the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the World is Enmity with God? Whoſoever therefore will be a Friend of the World, is the Enemy of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59359:61"/>God.</hi> He tells us here, That in St. <hi>James</hi>'s account, <hi>Our Heart is ſo much God's Property and Peculiar, and ought ſo intirely to be devoted to him, that 'tis a kind of Spiritual Adultery to admit any Creature into a Partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him in our Love.</hi> It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain theſe are not St. <hi>James</hi>'s words, and we have only Mr. <hi>N</hi>-'s Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that this is his ſenſe. But tho' Mr. <hi>N</hi>-'s affirming without any Proof, that all love of the Creature is here condemn'd, and ſaid to be a kind of Spiritual Adultery, needs no other Anſwer but a bare Negation; And the ſaying without any Proof, that it is only the inordinate love of the Creature that is ſo call'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, would be enough; Yet the context further plainly ſhows, that that is the meaning of St. <hi>James</hi> here, by what he calls Friendſhip of the World. To which let me add, that Adultery does not wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all other Love of any other Perſon; but a love that comes in competition, or invades that which
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59359:62"/>properly belongs to the Husband. For a Woman may love her Brother, or her Child, without being an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs; it being not with that Love that is due to her Husband. The laſt place Mr. <hi>N.</hi> cites to prove that Love of the Creatures is Sinful, is, from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. vi. 14. <hi>The World is Crucified to me, and I unto the World.</hi> Which laſt words, Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays <hi>at once comprize his preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that the Creature is not to be</hi> (in any degree) <hi>the Object of our love; with the very ſame ground and bottom upon which he has built it. For the Apoſtle here firſt of all ſuppoſes the World to be Crucified, that is to be a Dead, Unactive, Silent, and Quieſcent thing, in reſpect of himſelf; as not being able to operate upon him, or affect his Soul with any Sentiment as an Efficient Cauſe: And then in conſequence of that declares himſelf to be alſo Crucified to the World,</hi> p. 68. which Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains very truly (tho' not very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formably to his Opinion) <hi>by being inſenſible to all its Charms:</hi> For, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59359:62"/>to his Explanation, St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew very well that the World had no Charms. But whoſoever will read this whole Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> will evidently ſee that it amounts to this; That there were ſome Men ſo Preach'd Chriſt, as yet to have regard to the favour and good liking of Men; That they might avoid Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſome, and gain Glory from others: But St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Preaching of the Goſpel, had ſo intirely given up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to it, that he minded nothing but the Preaching of the Goſpel; Going on in that Work, without any regard either to Perſecution, or Vain-Glory. And thus the World was Crucified to him, and he to the World: They were as Dead things, and in this reſpect had no Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words are, <hi>As many as deſire to make a fair ſhew in the Fleſh, they conſtrain you to be Circumcis'd; Only, leſt they ſhould ſuffer Perſecution for the Croſs of Chriſt. For neither They themſelves, who are Circumcis'd, keep the Law; But de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have you Circumcis'd, that they may glory in your Fleſh. But God forbid that I ſhould Glory, ſave in the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whereby the World is Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to me, and I unto the World.</hi> Very often it happens, that a piece of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or as here, even a piece of a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59359:63"/>Verſe, ſerves for a Quotation, much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the whole would do. This is ſo evident in this Place, that it requires ſome Charity to think that a Man is in earneſt fearching after Truth, or believes himſelf, whilſt he is a Writing after ſuch a manner.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Character Mr. <hi>N.</hi> bears ought to be a Warrant for his Sincerity, we muſt conclude, that he does think St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that ſome would have them Circumcis'd only that they might avoid Perſecution, and might Glory in their Fleſh. But God forbid that he ſhould Glory in any thing but the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by which the Creatures are only the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional, not the Efficient Cauſes of his Pleaſing Senſations; and he Dead to them. This Mr. <hi>N.</hi> it ſeems, does think was the Senſe of what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid: But that it was not, I think common Senſe will ſufficiently ſatisfie us, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting Interpreters about it.</p>
            <p>Theſeare the Texts brought by Mr. <hi>N.</hi> to ſupport an Opinion grounded on an Hypotheſis, perhaps Demonſtrably falſe; That has evidently no proof, but the poor one from our Ignorance, that yet is not at all help'd by this Hypotheſis: Which is (therefore) as well as for the Ends
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59359:63"/>of Morality, plainly uſeleſs. Yet all this might well be Pardon'd to any Effort of advancing our Knowledge, if it did not pretend to influence our Religion; And not only ſo, but to be the very Baſis, and Foundation of Chriſtianity, as it is made to be by the firſt Ingenious Inventor of it. Mr. <hi>N.</hi> has not, indeed, advanced that ſo directly: But with more Confidence a great deal, making it the ground of Morality, he falls as little ſhort of it as is poſſible. And his Diſcourſes upon this Subject being in a more Popular way, are more likely to do hurt. For certainly to perſwade Men that God requires what they find impoſſible to perform, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to their very Conſtitution and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this World, is to make Religion, and the Teachers of it, ridiculous to ſome; And to drive others weaker, but better-minded People into Deſpair; By giving them occaſion to think that they do not love God as they ought. Such Effects, I fear, may be the Conſequences of Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s Doctrine, who teaches that we do not love God as we ought, whilſt we love any Creature at all: And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the above-cited Sermon, He poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſays, That <hi>the Creatures are no more our Goods, than our Gods; and that we may as well worſhip them, as love them.</hi> Pract. Diſc. <hi>p.</hi> 62.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:59359:64"/>
            <p>Theſe Opinions of Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſeem alſo to indanger the introducing, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe whoſe Imaginations are ſtronger than their Reaſon, a Devout way of talking; which having no ſober, and intelligible ſenſe under it, will either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably by degrees beget an Inſenſibility to Religion, in thoſe themſelves who uſe it, as well as others; By thus accuſtoming them to handle Holy things without Fear; Or elſe will turn to as wild an Enthuſiaſm as any that has been yet ſeen; and which can End in nothing but Monaſteries, and Hermitages; with all thoſe Sottiſh and Wicked Superſtitions which have accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied them where-ever they have been in uſe. And this the Author of the <hi>Chriſtian Converſations</hi> foreſaw very well muſt be the Conſequence; Or rather conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to his Religion and Profeſſion, might perhaps have it in his View and Deſign, to juſtifie thoſe things by this his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis; which makes them not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, but of neceſſary uſe. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that were, he concludes his Diſcourſe of our being obliged to have no Love for any Creature, with a ſincere Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment that if this be true (which he has concluded it is) it is then abſolutely neceſſary to renounce the World, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our ſelves to Woods and Deſarts:
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59359:64"/>For it is impoſſible to live in the daily Commerce and Converſation of the World, and love God as we ought to do. And accordingly he makes his Young Men, introduced to be Converts to Religion upon theſe Principles, bid Adien to the World, even to their Deareſt Friends, and Relations.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Pere Malebranche,</hi> it ſeems, was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with that <hi>Diſtinction</hi> which Mr. <hi>N.</hi> ſays, <hi>ought to be made of Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Soul, and Movements of the Body.</hi> Otherwiſe he might have aſſured his <hi>Ariſtarchus,</hi> that he was in a very great Miſtake, to believe that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples before laid down, obliged him to any retreat from the World, or Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of the Injoyments of it: Since <hi>the Movements of the Body</hi> (Mr. <hi>N.</hi> tells us) <hi>may be determin'd by thoſe Objects which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viron it; and by thoſe Movements,</hi> Ariſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus <hi>might have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited himſelf to thoſe things which were the Natural or Occaſional Cauſes of his Pleaſure.</hi> (See Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Philoſophical</hi> and <hi>Divine,</hi> p. 75.) But <hi>Pere Malebranche</hi> deſigning his Notions to be of ſome uſe to the World purſued them, whether by juſt conſequence they led him; and ſought not for any contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to make them inſignificant to any other Purpoſe than to ſhew the <hi>Partu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riency</hi>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:59359:65"/>of their Author. He therefore rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably from his Principles, inſiſts upon it, that the retreat from the World, is beſt for all; and neceſſary to moſt who deſign to lead a Chriſtian Life; Thoſe <hi>being much to be pitied whom God calls to live in the World for the Converſion of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This in a Papiſt, and one of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Order amongſt them, cannot ſeem ſtrange. But there can certainly be no greater Diſparagement to Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than to ſay; That it unfits Men for Society; That we muſt not only li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally become Fools for Chriſt's ſake; but alſo ceaſe to be Men. Can any Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Man, not bred up in the Bigottry of Popery, ever perſwade himſelf that ſuch a Religion can be from God? Or is there any appearance throughout the whole New Teſtament of its being ſo? <hi>John,</hi> indeed, who had not the power of Miracles, or a Voice from Heaven to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize his Miſſion, made himſelf be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, by the remarkable Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Life: But he neither Preach'd it, nor propos'd himſelf, in that, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to others. He was by ſomething extraordinary (tho' without Miracles) to draw Auditors to him, whom he might prepare to receive the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> But that living in a Deſart, and bidding adieu to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59359:65"/>Society, were not neceſſary to Religion, our Saviour's Example, as well as his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, ſhow. He came Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Converſing in the World like other Men: And he aſſures us, That <hi>he came not to deſtroy, but to fulfil the Law;</hi> viz. The Moral Law, which is the ſame with the Law of Reaſon; than which, <hi>Heaven and Earth, ſhall ſooner paſs away;</hi> and in which are legibly found thoſe Duties of an active and ſocial Life, that have ſo much recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and eterniz'd the Memories of many Philoſophers, and Lawgivers, and other great Men of Antiquity; Whoſe Religion Mankind would be apt to think they had reaſon to wiſh for again, if they were perſwaded that Chriſtianity were oppoſite to, and inconſiſtent with thoſe admired and beneficial Virtues that Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and Profit Society.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more evident than that Mankind is deſign'd for a Sociable Life. To ſay that Religion unfits us for it, is to reproach the Wiſdom of God as highly as it is poſſible; And to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent Religion as the moſt miſchievous thing in the World, diſſolving Societies. And there could not be a greater Artifice of the Devil, or Wicked Men to bring Chriſtianity into contempt than this. But it is to be hoped, that where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59359:66"/>are allow'd to be read, this can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prevail; And that thoſe who are not in danger of being led into it by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions of Prieſt-Craft, will not be impos'd upon in it by vain Philoſophy: Nor can there be any ſtronger Evidence, that (That Notion, of the Love of God, grounded on his Being the immediate Cauſe of all our Senſations) is falſe, than this, <hi>viz.</hi> That it Deſtroys all the Duties and Obligations of Social Life. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is not Mr. <hi>N</hi>'s deduction from thence, But it is that of his Oracle <hi>Pere Malebranche,</hi> and that of Reaſon; And he will ſcarce be believ'd to be Sincere, that ſhall ſay he can daily ſee and injoy the Creatures as Goods, without deſiring them as ſuch; Or that ſhall deny, that if it be our Duty not to deſire any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it muſt then neceſſarily be our Duty (as <hi>P. M.</hi> expreſly ſays it is) to have as little communication with them as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; and to betake our ſelves to Deſarts. But whether it were that Mr. <hi>N.</hi> has no inclination to this way of Living, and that it is to That that we owe his Happy Invention of Seeking, and injoying the good things of the World, without lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; Or that he was afraid by owning his Opinion (that we are obliged to renounce the World and live in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59359:66"/>Woods) He ſhould be ſuſpected of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Popiſh Superſtition; He can ſcarcely be preſum'd not to ſee that this inevitably follows from the Hypotheſis he has embraced. But yet how injurious ſoever this Conſequence is to Religion, ſo much is not therefore deny'd to what <hi>Per. Malebranche</hi> largely inſiſts upon, <hi>viz.</hi> That Retirement is ſometimes uſeful, if not neceſſary to a Chriſtian Life. Thoſe who live always in the hurry of the World, and the avocations of Worldly Buſineſs, without giving themſelves time, and retreat, frequently to reflect, being no doubt very likely to enter too much into the Spirit of it; We inſenſibly giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up our ſelves to, and uniting our Hearts with what we are conſtantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in, and with delight apply our ſelves to. But if in oppoſition to this, any one ſhould run into the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, of retreating wholly from all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and converſation with Men; And ſhould give themſelves the Happineſs <hi>Pere Malebranche</hi> ſpeaks of, of <hi>attending Eternity in Deſarts;</hi> it is to be fear'd they would not mend the Matter. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Vices they might part with by it, they muſt neceſſarily oppoſe thereby, one great end that they were ſent into the World for, <hi>viz.</hi> of doing good; By be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59359:67"/>wholly uſeleſs to others: And ſuch a one would certainly, by ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of all commerce with Men, be likelier to grow Wild, than improve the great Virtue of Chriſtianity, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of Humane Nature, Good Will, Charity, and the being Uſeful to others.</p>
            <p>As for Monaſteries, and Religious Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (as they are call'd) all who are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them, know that they are nothing leſs than what is pretended; And ſerve only to draw in Diſcontented, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout People, with an imaginary Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For there is conſtantly as much Pride, Malice, and Faction, within thoſe Walls, as without them; And (if we may believe what is ſaid, and has not wanted farther Evidence) very often as much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, our Natures are ſo ſuited to a mediocrity in all things, that we can ſcarce exceed in any kind with Safety, To be always buſy in the Affairs of the World, or always ſhut up from them, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be born: Always Company, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Solitude, are Dangerous: And ſo are any other Extreams.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59359:67"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
